マラウイに住む16歳のリサは
After watching the 2020 regional convention
2020年の地区大会を
in her native language of Chichewa,
16-year-old Lisa from Malawi stated:
母語のチェワ語で見た後
こう言いました
「この大会でエホバが
“With this convention, I saw
how Jehovah fulfilled his promise
『私は決してあなたを離れず
決してあなたを見捨てない』という
“at Hebrews 13:5:
ヘブライ 13:5の通りにして
くださったのが分かりました」
‘I will never leave you,
and I will never abandon you.’”
このように自分の言語で
大会を見たことへの感謝の言葉が
Many have made
similar appreciative comments
after watching the convention
in their language.
多数寄せられています
You have made kind donations online
皆さんがオンラインやその他の方法で
at donate.jw.org
惜しみなく
寄付してくださっていることに
and by other means.
感謝いたします
Thank you for these donations
それはとても多くの言語で
翻訳を行う上で助けになっています
that support
our extensive translation efforts.
先ほどのプログラムで
Earlier in our program,
we discussed five peace wreckers
平和を壊す5つのものを
「脱ぎ捨てる」ことについて考えました
that we should “put away.”
でも平和が乱された時
何ができるでしょうか
But what can we do
if peace has been disturbed?
Can it be restored, and if so, how?
どうすれば平和を取り戻せますか
We invite you to pay careful attention
どうぞ4部から成る次のシンポジウムを
to the following four-part symposium.
注意深くお聞きください
Brother John Ekrann, a helper
to the Coordinators’ Committee,
調整者委員会の援助者
ジョン・エクラン兄弟が
最初の話をしてくださいます
will start us off with the talk
“‘Seek Peace and Pursue It’ . . .
「『平和を願い 追い求めよ』
By Not Quickly Taking Offense.”
すぐに腹を立てない」です
このシンポジウムのテーマは
「平和を願い 追い求めよ」です
The title of this series of four talks
is “Seek Peace and Pursue It,”
and it’s based on 1 Peter 3:11.
ペテロ第一 3:11に基づいて
いるので そこを読みましょう
Let’s read that together
—1 Peter 3:11:
ペテロ第一 3:11
“Let him turn away from what is bad
and do what is good;
「悪から離れて善を行え
let him seek peace and pursue it.”
平和を願い 追い求めよ」
平和を追い求める必要があります
Yes, we have to pursue peace,
and pursuit requires effort.
それは簡単ではありません
Have you ever had to chase a piece
of paper that was in your hands
手に持っていた紙が風に飛ばされて
しまった という経験がありますか
and got blown away by the wind,
and just once you get to it,
the wind blows it away again and again?
追い掛けて拾おうとすると
また飛んでいってしまいます
It can really take quite some effort
紙を取り戻すにはかなりの努力が
必要かもしれません
to retrieve and get that paper
back in your hands.
Just standing there and watching
the paper blow farther and farther away
何もせずに ただ飛んでいく紙を
眺めているだけでは
それを取り戻すことはできません
is not going to get it back.
Well, peace can be a lot like that paper.
平和もその紙に似ています
At some point, it can get blown away,
いわば飛んでいってしまうことが
あります
and we have to then chase,
そうなると 追い掛ける または
追い求めなければ 取り戻せません
or pursue, it to get that peace back again.
これから 平和を追い求める方法を
4つ考えます
This series of talks will help us
to pursue peace in four ways:
by not quickly taking offense,
すぐに腹を立てないこと
by apologizing,
謝ること
by forgiving freely,
気持ちよく許すこと
and by using our gift of speech wisely.
そして よく考えて話すことです
Let’s consider our first way to pursue peace:
では 平和を追い求める
1つ目の方法を考えましょう
Avoid quickly taking offense.
すぐに腹を立てないことです
Now, because we are imperfect,
私たちは不完全なので 誤解して
すぐに腹を立てることがあります
we might misjudge others
and quickly take offense.
Notice that we say quickly take offense.
ここで注目したいのは
「すぐに」という言葉です
That’s an important word.
We need to avoid jumping
to conclusions quickly
まだ事実がよく分からないのに
すぐに決め付けるべきではありません
before we actually have the facts.
Even faithful men like Jesus’ apostles
have taken offense too quickly.
イエスの使徒たちも すぐに
腹を立ててしまったことがあります
You may recall the time that Jesus
and his apostles
ある時 イエスと使徒たちは
サマリア人の村で泊まれる所を
探していました
were looking for lodging
in a Samaritan village.
Now, the Samaritans in that village
rudely denied them lodging.
しかし サマリア人たちは
全く歓迎しませんでした
At Luke 9:54-56,
それで ルカ 9:54-56で
ヤコブとヨハネはイエスにこう言います
the apostles—James and John—
say to Jesus:
“Lord, do you want us to call fire down
from heaven and annihilate them?”
「主よ⋯⋯天から火が下るよう求めて
彼らを滅ぼし尽くしましょうか」
でもイエスは 2人の性急で
乱暴な言動を𠮟りました
But Jesus rebukes them for their
rash and rather violent suggestion.
Think of the serious consequences
もしイエスが 怒り立ったヤコブと
ヨハネのしたいようにさせていたら
had Jesus yielded to the violent temper
of James and John.
どうなっていたでしょうか
The Samaritans could have become
prejudiced against the Kingdom message.
サマリア人は良い知らせに
心を閉ざしたことでしょう
Instead, Jesus pursues a peaceful solution.
幸いなことに イエスは
平和を追い求めました
The account says
‘they simply went to a different village.’
そこを去って 別の村に
行くことにしたのです
Now, does this mean we’re saying
we can never take offense?
では 絶対に腹を立てては
いけないのでしょうか
No, you may have a legitimate
“cause for complaint.”
いいえ 正当な理由がある場合も
あるでしょう
The key point is that we should not
quickly draw conclusions
でも すぐにこうだと
決め付けるのではなく
事実を十分に確かめることが大切です
before we hear all the facts.
Proverbs 18:13 says:
格言 18:13にはこうあります
“When anyone replies to a matter
before he hears the facts,
「（話を十分に）聞かないうちに
返事をする人は
愚かであり 辱められる」
it is foolish and humiliating.”
In the following dramatization,
次のビデオを見ながら
すぐに腹を立てないために
note what helps one sister
to overlook an offense.
どんなことが役立つか考えましょう
そんな人だと思わなかった
And I expected more from you.
ヘイリー 何があったの？
Haley, what are you talking about?
Gossiping about my posts!
うわさしてたでしょ！私の投稿のことで
さみしいからって
ほかにすることないんですか？
Are you that lonely
that you’ve got nothing better to do?
Haley,
ヘイリー
ねえ ちょっと待って！
何の話をしてるの？
wait, please!
I don’t know what’s happening.
私の投稿のこと
エミリーと話しましたよね
Did you talk to Emily about my posts?
うん 話したけど
Yes, we did . . .
やっぱりうわさしてたんだ
So you gossiped about me.
No, I would . . .
うわさなんかしてない・・・
I looked up to you!
尊敬してたのに！
I would never . . .
私はただ・・・
You’re supposed to be the mature one,
立派な姉妹のはずが エミリーと
変わらないじゃないですか
and you’re just like Emily,
busy running your mouth.
あることないこと言って
Haley!
ヘイリー！
Look, I can see you’re upset,
ねえ 怒りたい気持ちは分かる
but trust me,
this is a huge misunderstanding.
でも聞いて 何か誤解してる
I love you.
ヘイリー あなたのこと
大事に思ってる
I would never ever say anything
behind your back.
だから私は絶対に
そんなこと言ったりしない
So please calm down.
ね 落ち着いて
Sometimes I just feel so alone
時々 独りぼっちに感じるんです
おばあちゃんのお世話と仕事で
—between Nana and work—
and then knowing all of you
are talking about me.
しかも みんなにうわさされてる
そんなことないから 信じて
I promise, that’s not what happened.
You’re just really tired and overwhelmed.
本当に疲れるし 大変だよね
So why don’t we
just slow things down a little.
ちょっとゆっくり落ち着こうか
集会に出ると 元気が出るよね
You know, meetings
always make me feel better,
even on my worst days.
元気がないときも
Why don’t we go inside,
じゃあ 中に入って涙拭いてこよう
clean up a little,
and enjoy the program together.
で 一緒に座ろっか
Then afterward, we can all talk.
集会の後 3人で話そう
大丈夫 きっと大丈夫だから
I promise, it’ll be OK.
ヘイリーは怒ってましたね
Haley really was upset.
She had already concluded that she
was being gossiped about by everyone.
会衆のみんなにうわさされていると
思い込んでいました
If we find ourselves
like Haley feeling offended,
もしヘイリーのような状況に置かれたら
どうすればすぐに
腹を立てずに済むでしょうか
how can we avoid quickly taking offense?
Well, we must stop and think.
落ち着いてよく考えることです
Let’s read Ecclesiastes 7:9
役立つアドバイスが
伝道の書 7:9にあるので
for some very good advice
in these situations
そこを読んでみましょう
—Ecclesiastes 7:9:
伝道の書 7:9
“Do not be quick to take offense,
「すぐに腹を立ててはならない
for the taking of offense lodges
in the bosom of fools.”
腹立ちは愚かな人の胸にとどまる」
Like Celia said in the parking lot to Haley,
セリアがヘイリーに伝えたように
“Please calm down.”
まず落ち着きましょう
So in those situations,
そして 自分は本当に
you need to think about what you know
全ての事実を知っているだろうか
ということをよく考えましょう
and, just as important, what you don’t know.
Now, you know what you were told happened,
こんなことがあった と聞いたとしても
but what was really said?
それは事実でしょうか
In the video,
Haley quickly believed what she was told.
ヘイリーは 悪いうわさをされたと
思い込んでいました
She did not even ask Celia
what she really said.
何があったかセリアに
確かめませんでした
Or you may know what was said,
話された内容は知っていても
but do you know what was
really meant by it?
相手の意図はどうでしょうか
Haley asked,
“Did you talk about . . . my posts?”
ヘイリーは 自分のことを話したか尋ね
And Celia said, “Yes.”
セリアが話したと言うと
すぐに悪いうわさだと決め付けました
And immediately, Haley assumed the worst.
Or perhaps we misjudged
the person who hurt us.
相手の人格を
否定してしまうこともあります
Haley misjudged Celia
on the spot by saying,
ヘイリーは セリアがエミリーと
同じぐらいひどいと言い放っていました
‘You’re just as bad as Emily.’
She had not even heard from Celia yet.
セリアの言い分も聞かずにです
Haley said to Celia
that she was the mature one,
立派な姉妹だと思って
セリアを尊敬していたのに
the one she looked up to,
yet she was quick to believe
the worst about her.
すぐに悪い人だと決め付けていました
Haley had not stopped
and really thought about what
落ち着いてよく考えなかったので
ひどいことを言ってしまいました
she was thinking and saying.
余裕がなかったのかもしれません
Perhaps she was having a hard day.
セリアは私たちにとって良い手本です
Well, Celia really set a fine example for us.
Even though Haley spoke harshly to her,
ヘイリーにひどいことを言われましたが
落ち着いてヘイリーの話を聞きました
Celia was calm and listened to Haley.
As Haley explained how
she was feeling lonely,
ヘイリーが おばあちゃんの
お世話などで大変で
dealing and caring for her grandmother,
独りぼっちに感じる と言うと
you can see the love and concern
that Celia had for Haley,
セリアは愛や気遣いを表していました
even though just moments before
she had spoken really harshly to her.
ひどいことを言われた
すぐ後でしたが 親切でした
Well, besides taking time
to think things through,
さて 落ち着いてよく考えることに
加えて 覚えておくとよいのは
we also need to remember
that it is Jehovah’s opinion of us
エホバからどう見られているかが
一番大事だということです
that matters the most.
Now, that’s an important point,
especially when we deal
これは特に 誤解されたり
不当な非難を受けたりした時に大切です
with misunderstandings
or false accusations.
Think about it:
Jehovah is an eyewitness to everything.
エホバは全てを見ている ということを
覚えておきましょう
To illustrate that, I want you to imagine
少し例えで考えてみましょう
あなたが交通事故に遭ったとします
you had a traffic accident.
Now, you were just sitting at the stop sign,
あなたが停車していたところ
別の車が勢いよく突っ込んできました
but another car ran straight into you.
The police come,
and the person that ran into you
警察が来ると 相手のドライバーは
あなたが突っ込んできたと言います
says that you ran into them,
and the police believe them.
そして 警察はそれを信じます
You take the matter to court.
裁判になります
The judge listens as the other person
says that you ran into them;
相手のドライバーは裁判官にも
あなたが突っ込んできたと言います
however, before you can say anything,
しかし あなたが何も言わないうちに
裁判官はこう言います
the judge says:
“No, that is not what happened.
「いいえ それは事実と違います
“I was there walking on the sidewalk
across the street that day,
私はちょうどあの時近くを歩いていて
事故の一部始終を見ていました」
and I saw the whole thing.”
Well, it’s extremely unlikely
that you can go to court and expect
もちろん 実際の裁判では
裁判官が目撃証人だということは
まずないでしょう
the judge for your case
to have been an eyewitness.
This does illustrate, though,
the peace of mind that we can have
でも 例えの中の裁判官のように
エホバは全てを見ている と思うと
安心するのではないでしょうか
knowing that Jehovah is an eyewitness
to all that happens.
So when falsely accused
or when we have a misunderstanding
では 不当に非難されたり
誤解がなかなか
解けなかったりするような場合には
that we cannot seem to clear up,
it is of great comfort for us to know
エホバが事実をご存じだということを
思い起こしましょう
that Jehovah was there that day
and saw the whole thing.
エホバは必ず全てを見ているからです
We don’t need to take offense
at every negative thing
何か気に障ることがあるたびに
すぐ腹を立てるべきではありません
that is said or done around us
or feel we have to defend ourselves
as being right on every occasion.
いつも自分の正しさを証明しようと
するべきでもありません
We would surely wear out emotionally
そうすると精神的に疲れてしまいますし
and probably not have very many friends.
周りの人から
煙たがられてしまうかもしれません
We should be willing
to overlook minor transgressions.
相手の軽い落ち度を
見過ごすようにしましょう
Let’s look at Proverbs 19:11
格言 19:11を開いてみましょう
—Proverbs 19:11.
格言 19:11
What can help us?
何とありますか
“The insight of a man
certainly slows down his anger,
「洞察力があればすぐに怒ることはない
and it is beauty on his part
to overlook an offense.”
過ちを見過ごす人は美しい」とあります
So can you “overlook an offense”?
では「過ちを見過ご」せますか
As the proverb said,
that ‘is beauty on our part.’
そうできる人は「美しい」と
書かれています
If not and you have
a serious cause for complaint,
もし見過ごせないような問題が
起きたとしても
handle matters
according to Jehovah’s direction.
エホバの指示に従って行動しましょう
Show insight.
洞察力を示して
すぐに怒らないようにしてください
Slow down any anger.
Think carefully, and listen patiently
相手の話を聞いて よく考えましょう
to make sure you clearly have all the facts
すぐに腹を立てるのではなく
まず 事実をよく
確かめるようにしましょう
before you become offended
or take action.
持っていた紙が風に飛ばされたという
例えを思い出してください
Remember that piece of paper
that you had in your hands
and got blown away by the wind?
それが1万円札だったらどうですか
What if it was a hundred-dollar bill?
Well, you would make every effort
大金なので もちろん必死になって
追い掛けるに違いありません
to pursue it and get it back
because it’s valuable.
どんな紙幣よりも 平和の方が
はるかに価値があります
Our peace with our brothers
is far more valuable than paper money.
When our peace
with our brothers or sisters
もし何らかの誤解や過ちなどによって
is blown away
by misunderstandings, mistakes, or sin,
兄弟姉妹との平和な関係が
吹き飛ばされたら
ぜひ平和を追い求めて
取り戻すようにしましょう
then we should pursue peace
and try hard to get it back.
すぐに腹を立てないことによって
Yes, we glorify God and promote peace
私たちは平和をつくる人になり
神をたたえることができるのです
when we avoid quickly taking offense.
人事委員会の援助者
ラルフ･ウォールズ兄弟が
Brother Ralph Walls,
a helper to the Personnel Committee,
will now present the next talk
of this symposium,
シンポジウムの次の話をします
“‘Seek Peace and Pursue It’
. . . By Apologizing.”
主題は 「『平和を願い
追い求めよ』 謝る」
“I am so sorry.”
「本当にごめんなさい」
“It’s my fault, please forgive me.”
「私が悪かったです」
No matter how we phrase it,
言い方はいろいろありますが
謝るのは簡単ではありません
it can be difficult to apologize.
Why is that so challenging?
どうしてでしょうか
There are many reasons:
例えば 相手に責められるのが
怖いと思うかもしれません
We may fear confrontation,
blame, or rejection.
Perhaps we feel embarrassed,
and we’re too proud to apologize.
プライドが邪魔をして
謝れないこともあります
We may reason, ‘Apologizing will not undo
the blunder I’ve already made.’
あるいは 謝っても状況は
変わらないと思うかもしれません
And it may even be that we are angry.
自分が腹を立てていることも
あるでしょう
This is such a matter of concern
ある興味深い例があります
that “in July 2000,
米国カリフォルニア州議会は
2000年7月に
1つの法案を可決しました
“the California State Legislature
in the United States
“passed a bill designed
to relieve people of liability
その法案によれば
事故を起こしてしまった場合
けがをさせてしまった相手に
謝罪の気持ちを表せば
“if they express sympathy to an individual
who was injured in an accident
“in which they
themselves were involved. . . .
責任が軽減されます
“It was noted that . . . people
often hesitate to extend an apology
なぜこの法律が制定されたかというと
謝罪すると裁判で不利になると考えて
謝罪しない人が多いからです
“[out of concern that]
it could be construed in court
as an admission of guilt.”
The Bible provides an account
of a faithful servant,
では 聖書に出てくる例に
注目してみましょう
the apostle Paul,
使徒パウロは 謝るという点で
良い手本を残しています
who was a good example
of one who apologized.
The account is
in the book of Acts chapter 23.
使徒 23章に書かれている出来事です
The setting: A Roman military officer
この時 ローマの軍司令官が
パウロがユダヤ人たちに訴えられている
理由を知りたいと思いました
wanted to know why Paul
was being accused by the Jews.
So he brought Paul
to the Jewish chief priests
それでパウロを
祭司長たちの所に連れていき
ユダヤ人たちの高等法廷である
サンヘドリンに集合を命じました
and commanded the Sanhedrin,
the high court, to assemble.
As we read Acts 23:1-5 together,
ご一緒に使徒 23:1-5を
読みましょう
we can’t help but be impressed
ここでパウロは 自分が正しいと
思っていることを
by Paul’s boldness
as he stands for what is right.
非常に大胆に語っています
But at the same time,
please take note of his humility.
でもそれだけでなく
謙遜さにも注目しましょう
Acts 23:1: “Looking intently
at the Sanhedrin,
1節から
「パウロはサンヘドリンの人々を
じっと見ながら言った
“Paul said: ‘Men, brothers,
『皆さん 兄弟たち
私は今日まで 神の前で良心に全く
やましいところなく行動してきました』
“‘I have behaved before God
“with a perfectly clear conscience
down to this day.’
“At this the high priest Ananias
すると大祭司アナニアが
パウロの口を打つようにと⋯⋯命じた
“ordered those standing by him
to strike him on the mouth.
“Then Paul said to him:
そこでパウロは⋯⋯言った
『白く塗った壁よ
“‘God is going to strike you,
you whitewashed wall.
あなたは神に打たれます
“‘Do you sit to judge me according to the Law
律法に従って⋯⋯
裁くために座っていながら
“‘and at the same time violate the Law
私を打つように命令して
律法を破るのですか』
“by commanding me to be struck?’
“Those standing by said:
そばに立っている人たちが言った
“‘Are you insulting the high priest of God?’
『おまえは神の大祭司を侮辱するのか』
“And Paul said: ‘Brothers,
パウロは言った 『兄弟たち
大祭司だとは知りませんでした
“‘I did not know he was high priest.
“‘For it is written,
“You must not speak injuriously
確かに 「民の支配者を悪く言っては
ならない」と書いてあります』」
of a ruler of your people.”’”
Paul immediately admitted his error.
パウロはすぐに間違いを認めました
What he had said,
裁く人は暴力に訴えるべきではない
という主張は正当なものでしたが
that the one appointed as judge
should not resort to violence, was right.
それでも不敬な態度を
取ったことを謝りました
Yet, he apologized.
In the following dramatization,
次のビデオの中で
we will see an older sister
年長の姉妹がテトス 2:3-5の
アドバイスを当てはめて
applying the inspired words of Titus 2:3-5
「健全な考え方」ができるように
若い姉妹たちを助けます
in order to advise younger sisters
“to be sound in mind.”
We will also observe
how one of the younger sisters
また 若い姉妹たちの1人が
avoids further problems
and pursues peace
問題をこじらせないように謙遜に謝る
ことによって平和を追い求めます
by humbly apologizing.
何でこんなことになったのかは
分からないけど
I don’t know how this happened
but, Haley, I’m sorry.
ヘイリー ごめんなさいね
It hurts me to see you so upset.
そんな気持ちに
なってるの見て つらいわ
I can’t believe you two.
2人とも信じられません
First,
まず あなたが聞いたことは
what you heard
私が言ったことじゃない
was not what I said.
姉妹がそう思ってるって
思ったから言っただけです
Well, I thought that was how you felt.
And even if I got that part wrong,
all this drama?
それが勘違いだったとしても
そんなに怒ることですか
Now stop!
エミリー！ねえ 2人とも
Come on, girls.
ヘイリーも こっちに来て
Haley, come closer.
“Love is patient and kind.”
「愛は辛抱強く 親切」
愛は嫉妬しない
It’s not jealous.
It doesn’t become provoked,
そして いら立たない
大変なことがあってもね
even when things become difficult.
So, what are we going to do?
じゃあ どうしたらいいかな？
I just thought if—
私はただ・・・
No,
いや ごめんヘイリー
I’m sorry, Haley.
I’m sorry.
ごめんなさい
I shouldn’t have judged you so harshly.
厳しく見過ぎてた
そんなふうに見るべきじゃなかった
I shouldn’t have judged you at all.
And I’m sorry for dragging you into this
by twisting what you said.
セリア姉妹 勝手なこと言って
巻き込んじゃって ごめんなさい
It’s OK; things happen.
大丈夫 そういうことあるわよね
私も経験あるわ
I’ve been on both ends.
I should never have spoken
that way to you, Celia
あんなこと言っちゃってごめんなさい
セリア姉妹
—I mean, to either of you.
というか 2人に対して
I’ve got to get home to Nana.
おばあちゃん待ってる 帰らなきゃ
I’ll call you tomorrow.
あした電話するわね
またね
Bye.
セリアは何も悪くありませんでしたが
それでも謝りました
The older sister apologized,
even though she was not in the wrong.
She also urged
the two younger sisters to make peace.
そして姉妹たちに
和解するよう促しました
It takes courage, humility,
and determination to apologize.
謝るには 勇気や謙遜さや
決意が必要です
It’s interesting to note what’s stated
フィリピ 2:3にとても役立つ考えが
書かれているので
at Philippians 2:3:
そこを読んでみましょう
“Do nothing out of contentiousness
or out of egotism,
「対抗心を抱いたり 自己中心的に
なったりしてはなりません
but with humility
consider others superior to you.”
謙遜になり 自分より他の人の方が
上だと考えてください」
ここから分かるように 私たちは相手を
言い負かそうとするべきではありません
That means our determined effort
is not to win an argument,
which could be contentious,
nor do we want to start a discussion
また 相手と話し合う時に
with the primary thought being
that we are in the right.
自分の正しさを証明しようと
すべきでもありません
That could mean
that we are self-concerned, or egotistical.
それは自己中心的な考え方に
なってしまいます
Rather, in harmony
with the principle of that scripture
ぜひ今読んだ聖句を思いに留めて
謙遜に行動するようにしましょう
we want to act with humility.
Our aim should be to pursue peace.
大事なのは平和を追い求めることです
Even if we think the other person
is being unreasonable,
たとえ相手の態度や振る舞いに
納得がいかなくても
we apologize.
謝りましょう
平和はなぜ大切でしょうか
Why is it so important to do so?
Because that is what makes
our worship to Jehovah acceptable.
私たちの崇拝を
エホバに受け入れてもらうためです
At Matthew chapter 5,
マタイ 5:23, 24で
verses 23, 24,
イエスがそのことをどのように
説明しているか注目しましょう
Jesus makes it very clear:
「それで あなたが供え物を
祭壇に持ってきて
“If, then, you are bringing
your gift to the altar
仲間が自分に対して何か反感を
抱いていることをそこで思い出したなら
“and there you remember
that your brother has something against you,
“leave your gift there
in front of the altar,
供え物を祭壇の前に残して
出掛けていきなさい
“and go away.
“First make your peace with your brother,
まず仲間と仲直りし
and then come back and offer your gift.”
それから戻ってきて
供え物を捧げなさい」
“One Bible scholar
describes the scene this way:
この聖句をある聖書学者は
こう説明しています
“‘The worshipper has entered the Temple;
「崇拝者は神［殿］に入り
その一連の中庭 つまり異邦人の中庭
婦人の中庭を通り抜け
“‘he has passed through [a] series of courts,
“‘the Court of the Gentiles,
“‘the Court of the Women,
the Court of the Men.
男子の中庭に入った
“‘Beyond that there lay
the Court of the Priests
その男子の中庭の向こうには
平信徒は入れない祭司の中庭があった
“‘into which the layman could not go.
“‘The worshipper is standing at the rail,
崇拝者は柵のそばに立って
“ready to hand over
his [living animal] to the priest.’ . . .
［犠牲］をすぐ祭司に
引き渡せるよう［にしている］」
“At that [critical] moment,
その大事な時に 崇拝者は
仲間が自分に対して
反感を抱いていることを思い出します
the worshipper remembers
that his brother has something against him.”
どうすべきでしょうか
What is he to do?
“Leave your gift there
in front of the altar,”
イエスはこう言っています
「供え物を祭壇の前に残して
出掛けていきなさい」
Jesus explains, “and go away.”
What does Jesus say is more important
than offering up a sacrifice?
犠牲を捧げるよりも
大切なことは何でしょうか
‘First, make peace with your brother.
「まず仲間と仲直りし
それから戻ってきて 供え物を
捧げなさい」とイエスは言いました
‘Then when you have come back,
offer up your gift.’
The expression rendered “make your peace”
大切なのは仲直りすること
平和をつくることです
means “to reconcile.”
Jesus’ words teach a crucial lesson:
これはとても大事な教訓です
Reconciliation, or peace,
犠牲を捧げることよりも
平和を優先する必要があります
comes before sacrifice.
The way we treat fellow worshippers
もし仲間との関係が良くないなら
has a direct bearing
on our relationship with God.
神とも良い関係を持つことはできません
First John 4:20 pointedly says:
ヨハネ第一 4:20には
端的にこうあります
“For the one who does not love his brother,
whom he has seen,
「自分が見ている兄弟を愛さない人は
見たことがない神を
愛することはでき［ません］」
cannot love God,
whom he has not seen.”
If we find ourselves in a situation
where we have offended a fellow worshipper,
もし仲間の感情を
害してしまったことに気付いたなら
イエスの助言を当てはめましょう
we want to apply Jesus’ counsel.
We want to take the initiative
自分の方から行動し
仲直りするように努めましょう
to approach our brother or sister.
We may need
to acknowledge their hurt feelings.
相手の感情を思いやってください
We may also need to ask,
“What can I do to make amends?”
どうすれば関係を修復できるか
考えてください
Often a sincere apology
is all that is needed.
多くの場合 誠実に謝れば十分でしょう
Although our worship today
no longer includes animal sacrifices,
現代の私たちは 動物の犠牲を
捧げることはしません
what Jesus was teaching
でも イエスが強調したように
emphasizes that there is a connection
もし仲間との関係が平和でないなら
between peace with our brother
私たちの崇拝は神に
受け入れられなくなってしまいます
and acceptable worship to God.
When two humans are at odds,
2人の人が仲たがいした場合
大抵どちらにも落ち度があるものです
there may be a measure
of blame on both sides,
どちらも不完全で間違いをするからです
since both are imperfect and prone to error.
それで 互いに歩み寄る必要があります
This usually calls for mutual concessions.
Even if only the one apologizing is right,
謝っている側が正しい
ということもありますが
the issue is not so much
who is right and who is wrong
問題はどちらが正しいか
ということよりも
和解するために
どちらが率先するかということです
but who will take the initiative
to make peace.
When the apostle Paul heard
that the Christians in Corinth
使徒パウロは コリントの一部の
クリスチャンが仲たがいして仲間を訴え
were taking fellow servants of God
裁判ざたになっていることを聞いた時
こう言いました
to secular courts over personal differences,
he said:
“Why [do you] not
rather let [yourself] be wronged?
「なぜ不当な扱いを受けるままに
しないのですか
Why do you not
rather let [yourself] be defrauded?”
なぜだまし取られるままに
しないのですか」
要点は明らかです
The principle is clear.
Peace among fellow believers
is more important than proving
どちらが正しいかということよりも
仲間と平和な関係でいることの方が
重要なのです
who is right and who is wrong.
Keeping this in mind makes it easier
to apologize for a wrong
このことを覚えておくと 誰かが
誤解して感情を害している場合にも
that someone thinks
we’ve committed against him or her.
謝りやすくなるでしょう
A heartfelt apology can open the way
誠実に謝れば 互いに腹を割って
話し合うきっかけになります
to a constructive conversation.
It can minimize problems
そしてきっと問題を解決し
平和を取り戻せるでしょう
and restore peace.
Brother Leonard Myers,
執筆委員会の援助者
レナード・マイヤーズ兄弟が
a helper to the Writing Committee,
will now present
the next talk of this symposium,
このシンポジウムの
次の話をしてくださいます
“‘Seek Peace and Pursue It’ . . .
主題は 「『平和を願い 追い求めよ』
気持ちよく許す」
By Forgiving Freely.”
It’s a simple fact
that to be at peace with others,
誰かと平和な関係でいるためには
we must be willing to forgive.
許すことが大切です
2つの例を考えましょう
Please notice two examples:
1つ目は ある父親と娘の例です
A father and his teenage daughter
didn’t get along.
Minor disagreements often developed
into shouting matches.
2人はよく怒鳴り合いの
けんかをしていました
Finally, the tension got so bad
あまりにも険悪になったので
父親は娘を追い出しました
that the daughter was asked
to leave the house.
やがて娘は自分の間違いを認め
Eventually, she recognized
that she was at fault
and asked for her father’s forgiveness.
父親に許しを求めました
しかし 父親は態度を和らげず
But instead of overlooking her mistakes,
her father rejected her efforts.
娘を突き放しました
He was unwilling to extend forgiveness
to his own daughter.
自分の娘なのに
許そうとしなかったのです
Now, let’s contrast that
with another example.
では 2つ目の例を考えましょう
A blameless man was condemned to die
for a crime he didn’t commit.
ある男性が無実の罪で
処刑されることになりました
Shortly before he died,
the innocent man stated:
その人は死ぬ少し前にこう言いました
「父よ 彼らをお許しください ⋯⋯
“Father, forgive them,
for they do not know what they are doing.”
何をしているのか知らないのです」
Those words of Jesus
are recorded at Luke 23:34,
これは ルカ 23:34の
イエスの言葉です
and he may have been referring
to the Roman soldiers
「彼ら」とは誰のことでしょうか
who drove the nails into his hands and feet
イエスの手足にくぎを打ち込んだ
ローマの兵士たちのことかもしれません
and who didn’t know who he really was.
あるいは イエスの処刑を求めたものの
Or Jesus may have had in mind
some in the crowd
who demanded his execution
後に信仰を持つようになる
人たちのことかもしれません
but would later exercise faith in him.
いずれにしても イエスは人を
寛大に許すことをいといませんでした
The point is that Jesus
was willing to forgive freely.
How do we measure up
with regard to forgiveness?
では 私たちはどうでしょうか
Are we like Jesus,
willing to forgive others freely?
イエスのように人を
気持ちよく許すでしょうか
それとも 娘を許さなかった父親のよう
になってしまうことがあるでしょうか
Or at times, do we tend to be more
like the man who was unwilling to forgive?
許すのは簡単ではありません
Granting forgiveness isn’t always easy.
Imperfection exerts
a powerful influence over us,
私たちは不完全なので
うまく人に思いやりを
示せないことがあります
sometimes robbing us of compassion.
When someone hurts us,
傷つけられると 腹を立てたり
恨みを抱いたりするかもしれません
we may become resentful, or hold a grudge.
And perhaps some of us
were taught not to forgive others.
やられたらやり返せ と
教わった人たちもいます
ですから 確かに人を許すのは
難しいことがあります
Little wonder that cultivating
a peaceful, forgiving spirit
can be difficult.
それでも聖書は 人を寛大に
許すようにと言っています
Still, the Bible encourages us
to forgive freely.
人を許す点で ヨブの模範も
考えてみましょう
Let’s consider another example
of forgiveness in the man Job.
ヨブは大変な目に遭いましたね
Now, we’re familiar with his trials:
loss of his possessions and ten children,
財産と10人の子供を失い
ひどい病気になり
a loathsome disease,
and his wife told him to curse God and die.
妻にもきついことを言われました
3人の友人がヨブの災難について聞き
Three companions heard
about Job’s calamities,
and they agreed to go comfort him.
慰めに行きます
Job 2:13 states that when they arrived,
ヨブ 2:13によると
3人は「7日間ずっと ヨブと
一緒に⋯⋯座って」いましたが
“they sat . . . with him
for seven days and seven nights,”
「誰も話し掛け」ませんでした
but they didn’t say “a word to him.”
でも その方がましでした
Now, maybe that was a good thing
3人は口を開いたかと思えば
because when they finally opened
their mouths,
they deeply hurt Job
with their baseless accusations.
根拠のない非難をして
ヨブを傷つけたからです
But notice something interesting
about this account.
でもその後が興味深いので
Please turn with me to Job chapter 42.
ヨブ 42章を開いてみましょう
At the end of Job’s trials, Jehovah asked Job
エホバは ヨブのことを悪く言った
3人のために
to do something
regarding these false accusers.
あることをするようにヨブに言いました
Notice Jehovah’s words there at Job 42,
the {
ヨブ 42:8の後半の
エホバの言葉に注目しましょう
「私に仕えるヨブが
あなたたちのために祈る ⋯⋯
“And my servant Job will pray for you.
“I will surely accept his request
あなたたちを処罰しないで
ほしいと⋯⋯の願いを
not to deal with you
according to your foolishness.”
［私は］必ず聞き入れる」
いかがですか エホバはヨブに
Did you notice
that after all the false accusations,
自分を非難して苦しめた人たちの
ために祈るようにと言いました
Jehovah asked Job to pray
for the men who had tormented him?
Now, would Job tell Jehovah,
ではヨブはどうするでしょうか
“Jehovah, after what they said to me,
I’m not going to forgive them”?
「この3人を許すつもりは
ありません」と言うでしょうか
Would Job be resentful?
恨みを抱くでしょうか
Notice the latter portion of verse 9:
9節の後半には何とありますか
“And Jehovah accepted Job’s prayer.”
「エホバはヨブの祈りを聞き入れた」
Job followed Jehovah’s instructions.
ヨブは指示通りにしたのです
ヨブが忠誠を貫き 人を許した結果
どうなりましたか
What was the result
of Job’s integrity and his forgiving spirit?
10節
Verse 10:
“After Job had prayed for his companions,
「ヨブが友人たちのために祈った後
エホバはヨブの苦難を取り去り
“Jehovah removed Job’s tribulation
and restored his prosperity.
再び豊かな生活を送らせ⋯⋯
以前［の］物を 2倍にして与えた」
Jehovah gave him double what he had before.”
The account goes on to say
that Job had ten more children.
その後 ヨブにはまた
10人の子供が生まれ
さらに140年生きました
He lived for 140 more years,
17節にはこうあります
and verse 17 states:
“Finally Job died,
after a long and satisfying life.”
「ヨブは⋯⋯充実した日々を送り
やがて生涯を終えた」
Job was blessed for his forgiving spirit,
ヨブは人を許したので豊かに祝福され
and he set a good example for us
to forgive freely.
許す点で素晴らしい手本となっています
次のビデオの中で
In the following dramatization
with Celia and Haley,
ヘイリーがついにエミリーを許す
ことにした理由に注目しましょう
notice why Haley finally decides
to forgive freely.
ねえ 私だけど
Hey, it’s me.
I’ve been thinking of you.
どうしてる？
Great broadcast.
今月のブロードキャスティングの
オリジナルソング 良かったよね
How did you like the new original song?
電話くれる？
Give us a call.
I wish she’d give it a rest.
ああ もういい加減にしてよ！
Sorry?
何？
あっ 何でもないです
Oh, nothing.
すみません エミリーから
何万回もかかってきてて
Sorry, it’s just Emily
for the millionth time.
What’s the problem, love?
まだ何かあるの？
There’s no problem.
別に ないですけど・・・でも・・・
It’s just . . .
仲直りするの難しそう？
. . . difficult to let her back in?
Not that simple?
簡単じゃないよね
Not that simple.
簡単じゃないですね
You want to forgive . . .
許したいと思ってるんでしょう？
. . . but not get burned again.
でも・・・また傷つきたくない
Keep in mind
許すことは
that a chance to forgive
is a chance to imitate Jehovah.
エホバに倣うチャンスになるってこと
覚えておいて
そのチャンス 逃したくないよね
We wouldn’t want to miss that opportunity.
そんなふうに考えたこと なかったです
I never thought about it like that.
自分が許してもらいたいと
思った時のこと 思い出してみて
Think back to a time
when you wanted forgiveness
全てを本当に許してほしいと
思った時 どう感じた？
—when it meant everything.
How did it feel?
おばあちゃんもでしたよ
とっても心配されてましたよ
. . . just like your Nana does as well.
She really deeply cares about you.
みんなをがっかりさせて
You feel awful
that you’ve let everyone down.
すごく落ち込みました
大事に思ってるよ
You’re very precious.
ありがとう
Thank you.
みんなが許してくれて
Then they forgive you,
心が軽くなりました
and suddenly everything is OK.
Emily, sorry I haven’t been back to you.
エミリー
返事してなくてごめんね
あした予定ある？
Have plans for tomorrow?
セリアは上手に考えさせていましたね
What good reasoning on the part of Celia!
Did you notice the expression
that really touched Haley’s heart?
ヘイリーの心を打った言葉を
覚えていますか
“A chance to forgive
is a chance to imitate Jehovah.
「許すことは エホバに倣う
チャンスになる
そのチャンス 逃したくないよね」
We wouldn’t want to miss that opportunity.”
私たちも傷つけられた時
So when we’ve been wronged,
we don’t want to miss the opportunity
エホバに倣うチャンスだと考えて
to imitate Jehovah by forgiving freely.
寛大に許しましょう
Please notice how this is highlighted
at Colossians 3:13.
そのことがコロサイ 3:13で
強調されています
ヨブが 祈るようにというエホバの指示
に従ったことを思い起こしてください
When we considered Job’s example,
remember that Jehovah
instructed him to pray for his companions.
And that helped Job
display a forgiving spirit.
その指示はヨブの助けになりました
では コロサイ 3:13には
どんな指示があるでしょうか
Well, notice here what Jehovah
instructs us to do at Colossians 3:13:
“Continue putting up with one another
「引き続き互いに我慢し
“and forgiving one another freely
寛大に許し合いましょう
“even if anyone has a cause for complaint
against another.
たとえ誰かに不満を感じるとしてもです
“Just as Jehovah freely forgave you,
エホバが寛大に許して
くださったのですから
you must also do the same.”
同じようにしなければなりません」
ここで「寛大に許す」と訳されている
ギリシャ語は
The Greek verb used here for “freely forgive”
is related to a word often rendered
「惜しみない親切」や
「恵み」と関係がある言葉です
“undeserved kindness” or “favor.”
When used in the sense of forgiving,
このギリシャ語動詞は
「気前よく許す」とか
this verb conveys the idea of doing so
「惜しみなく許す」という考えを
伝えています
freely, generously
—just as when you, out of generosity,
give a gift to someone.
誰かに惜しみなく贈り物を
する時のような態度です
Jehovah requires that we
freely forgive others in imitation of him.
私たちには エホバに倣って
寛大に許すことが求められています
Did you notice the end of the verse?
節の最後に 「同じようにしなければ
なりません」とありますね
“You mu{
Now, if the offense is minor,
it’s best to overlook it.
相手のささいな過ちは
見過ごすのが最善です
コリント第一 13章には
First Corinthians 13:5 states
「愛は傷つけられても
根に持ちません」とあります
that love “does not keep account
of the injury.”
And Proverbs 19:11 tells us
格言 19:11にも
that “it is beauty . . .
to overlook an offense.”
「過ちを見過ごす人は
美しい」とあります
However, if we feel that we need to talk
to our brother or sister
でも 自分が傷ついたことを
相手に話す必要があると思える場合には
about an offense that was committed
against us,
どのようにすればいいでしょうか
what’s the best way to handle that?
まず エホバに祈って
導きを求めましょう
First, we should ask Jehovah in prayer
for his guidance.
Then with the brother’s good qualities
in mind,
それから相手の良いところを考えながら
誠実に自分の気持ちを伝えます
graciously tell him
that we want to make peace.
Listen carefully and empathetically.
相手の言うことをよく聞いてください
話を遮らずに 最後まで
きちんと聞くようにしましょう
We shouldn’t interrupt, even if we
don’t agree with everything being said.
It may be that his viewpoint is wrong,
but it is his viewpoint.
たとえ納得しにくくても
相手の見方を尊重します
自分が話す番になったら
優しく話しましょう
Then when it’s our turn to speak,
we want to be gracious.
Tell the brother
what we appreciate about him;
相手の良いところを褒めてください
apologize for any part that we played
in the misunderstanding.
自分にも落ち度があるかも
しれないので 謝りましょう
If our humble efforts result in good,
thank Jehovah.
もしうまく和解できたら
エホバに感謝できます
If they don’t,
keep asking Jehovah for guidance
うまくいかなかったなら
引き続きエホバに導きを求めつつ
while we look for another opportunity
to make peace.
別の機会にトライしましょう
When we truly forgive,
本当に相手を許したなら
we make a heartfelt decision
to let go of resentment.
もう憤りの気持ちを抱くことはしません
とても平和な気持ちになります
And what peace that can bring us!
Now, forgiving doesn’t mean
that we approve of a wrong action,
ただ 私たちは間違った行いを
容認したり 軽視したり
consider it unimportant,
or pretend it didn’t happen.
なかったことにしたりはしません
Also, if we’ve been treated unjustly
and have a cause for complaint,
また 不当な扱いを受けて
物事を正す必要があるなら
we do what we can to pursue peace
and resolve the matter.
平和を追い求めつつ解決を図ります
And then we confidently leave it
in Jehovah’s hands.
そして 後はエホバに委ねます
Brothers and sisters, what will you
take away from this consideration?
この話からどんなことを
学べたでしょうか
I’m sure you’ll agree that it can be
a challenge at times to forgive.
許すのが簡単ではないことは
確かにありますね
But rather than be like the man
we spoke of earlier
でも決して 娘を許さなかった
父親のようにはなりたくありません
who refused to forgive his own daughter,
may we follow the examples of Jehovah,
Jesus, Job, and Haley
ぜひ心掛けたいのは エホバ
イエス ヨブ ヘイリーの手本に倣って
by forgiving freely, generously.
寛大に許すことです
忘れないでください 許すことは
エホバに倣うチャンスになります
Remember, a chance to forgive
is a chance to imitate Jehovah,
そのチャンスを逃したくはありません
and we wouldn’t want to miss
that opportunity.
ぜひ気持ちよく許すよう努力して
May all of us pursue peace
by being willing to forgive freely.
平和を追い求めていきましょう
統治体のゲリト・レッシュ兄弟が
Brother Gerrit Lösch,
a member of the Governing Body,
シンポジウムの最後の話を
してくださいます
will now present the final talk
of this symposium,
“‘Seek Peace and Pursue It’ . . .
By Using Our Gift of Speech Wisely.”
主題は 「『平和を願い 追い求めよ』
よく考えて話す」
Why is it challenging
to use our gift of speech wisely?
私たちは時々
失言してしまうことがありますね
Because something powerful
constantly works against us.
なぜかというと あるものがいつも
邪魔をするからです 何でしょうか
What is it?
不完全さです
Imperfection.
The tongue is powerful.
私たちの舌には大きな力があり
人を元気づけることもあれば
It can do much good,
but because of imperfection,
不完全さのせいで
傷つけることもあります
it can also cause much harm.
そのことが聖書の「格言の書」で
よく説明されています
This thought is well expressed
in the Bible book of Proverbs.
For example, Proverbs 12:18 says:
例えば 格言 12:18には
こうあります
“Thoughtless speech
is like the stabs of a sword,
「心ない発言は剣のように突き刺し
but the tongue of the wise is a healing.”
賢い人たちの舌は人を癒やす」
And Proverbs 18:21 states:
18:21にはこうあります
“Death and life
are in the power of the tongue;
「死も命も舌の力に支配される
those who love to use it
will eat its fruitage.”
話すのが好きな人は
その結果を刈り取る」
Words have power,
言葉には大きな力があるので
何を言うか またどのように言うかに
so we need to be careful about what we say
よく気を付ける必要があります
and how we say it.
Perhaps you can recall
when someone spoke unkindly to you
もしかしたら 誰かに
不親切なことを言われて
深く傷ついたことがあるかもしれません
and hurt you deeply.
On the other hand, thoughtful speech
逆に 思いやりのある言葉によって
can mend an aching heart
and heal friendships.
傷ついた心が
癒やされたこともあるでしょう
Because of imperfection,
we all have difficulty
私たちは不完全なので
言葉に気を付ける必要があります
controlling our tongue.
This was true
even of the first-century disciple James.
イエスの弟子だったヤコブも
そのことを実感していました
自分が書いた手紙の第3章の中で
He humbly acknowledged the challenge
that all humans face
全ての人が直面する
難しい状況を取り上げています
in the third chapter of his inspired letter.
Notice how James described this
ヤコブ 3:3-6と8節で
at James 3:3-6, 8:
ヤコブがどんなことを述べているかに
注目しましょう
“If we put bridles in the mouths of horses
「馬を従わせるために
口にくつわをかませれば
“to make them obey us,
馬の体全体を操れます
“we guide also the whole body.
“Look also at ships: Although they are so big
船についても考えてください
船はとても大きく
強い風を受けて動きますが
“and are driven by strong winds,
“they are steered by a very small rudder
かじを取る人は
非常に小さなかじを使って
“wherever the man at the helm
is inclined to go.
思い通りに船を動かします
“So, too, the tongue
is a small part of the body,
同じように 舌は体の小さな部分ですが
“and yet it makes great brags.
大いに自慢します
ご存じの通り ごく小さな火が
大きな森を燃やしてしまいます
“See how small a fire it takes
“to set a great forest ablaze!
“The tongue is also a fire.
舌は火です
“The tongue represents a world
of unrighteousness
体の器官のうち
舌は不正で満ちています
“among our body members,
for it defiles
体全体を汚し
人の一生を燃やしてしまいます
“all the body
and sets the whole course of life on fire,
and it is set on fire by Gehenna.”
ゲヘナの火によって燃え立つのです」
8節 「舌を従わせることは
誰にもできません
And verse 8:
“But no human can tame the tongue.
“It is unruly and injurious,
舌は手に負えない有害なもので
死をもたらす毒で満ちています」
full of deadly poison.”
In addition to inherited imperfection,
不完全さだけでなく
私たちの生い立ちも話し方に影響します
our upbringing could also be a factor.
The Watchtower{
「ものみの塔」
2006年9月15日号の
page 21, paragraph 6 states:
21ページ6節には
こう述べられています
“In addition to human imperfection,
「人間の不完全さだけでなく家庭環境も
“family environment plays a role
in the misuse of the tongue.
良くない話し方をする原因の一つです
“Some people were raised in homes
『容易に合意しない 自制心のない
“where parents were ‘not open
to any agreement, . . .
粗暴な』親に育てられた人も
いるでしょう」
without self-control, fierce.’”
Despite such challenges,
it is possible for each one of us
確かにいろいろ大変なことはありますが
それでも「平和を願い
追い求め［る］」ことができます
to “seek peace and pursue it.”
Jesus set a good example
イエスは よく考えて話す点で
素晴らしい手本を示しています
in using the gift of speech wisely.
He used his speech to encourage
and comfort others.
いつも言葉で人を励まし 慰めました
While on earth, he applied to himself
the words
地上にいた時 イエスは
イザヤ 61:1の言葉を
自分自身に当てはめました
found at Isaiah 61:1,
which states the following:
こういう聖句です
「主権者である主エホバの聖なる力が
私の上にある エホバが私を選び
“The spirit of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah
is upon me,
“because Jehovah anointed me
to declare good news to the meek.
温厚な人に良い知らせを
告げるようにさせたからである
私は神から遣わされて
心が傷ついた人を癒やし
“He sent me to bind up the brokenhearted,
“to proclaim liberty to the captives
捕らわれている人に釈放を 囚人に
目が大きく開かれることを知らせる」
and the wide opening of the eyes
to the prisoners.”
As recorded at Matthew 12:20,
Matthew applies the words
マタイ 12:20から分かるように
マタイはイザヤ 42:1-3の言葉を
イエスに当てはめました
of Isaiah 42:1-3 to Jesus.
マタイ 12:20にこうあります
At Matthew 12:20, he stated:
“No bruised reed will he crush,
「彼は 傷ついたアシを折らず
“and no smoldering wick will he extinguish,
くすぶるランプの火を消さず
やがて確実に公正をもたらす」
until he brings justice with success.”
We learn an important lesson
from such verses.
こうした聖句から学べる
大切なこととして
イエスは舌に力があることを
よく分かっていました
Jesus recognized that the tongue has power
—power to harm and power to heal.
傷つける力や 癒やす力です
The Watchtower{
それで「ものみの塔」
2015年2月15日号の
page 13, and paragraph 11, thus stated
13ページ11節には
このように述べられています
that “Jesus showed discernment
「イエスは言葉と行動の両面で
常に識別力を示しました」
in all he said and did.”
Can we imitate Jesus more closely?
では どうすれば
イエスに倣えるでしょうか
If so, what will you do
the next time an opportunity arises
自分が何をどのように言うかによって
状況が大きく変わりそうな場面に
遭遇した時 どうしたいと思いますか
for you to use your gift of speech wisely?
In the following dramatization,
次のビデオを見ながら
よく考えて話すなら
notice how the wise use of the tongue
helps to heal.
人間関係が良くなることに
注目しましょう
ねえ ちょっと聞きたいんだけど
冬の新作 どれがいいと思う？
I just need a bit of help.
What do you think I should do
for my winter collection?
ああ どうだろう？
Well, I don’t know,
but I love what you did with your new stuff,
どれもほんとに
すごくかわいいと思うんだけど
especially
そうだね 私はこれが好き！
this set.
ああ ありがとう
Oh, thanks.
エミリーのアドバイス
すごい助かってる
You’ve all given me so many great ideas.
ヘイリー センスあるよ
Yeah, but you make them.
Yeah.
そうかな？
行きましょうか
OK, girls.
You love it.
分かる
Oh, this is my song.
ああ この歌好き
私も
Mine too.
“You have a treasured place
「さあ 踏み出して 迷わずに
“in Jehovah’s house;
“He’ll help you out [out].
エホバを見て 見て」
And you have . . .”
Oh, I sing like a crow.
ああ 本当に私の歌ひどい
No, stop!
そんなことないですよ
これ ほかにも歌ってる人いたんだけど
I’ll tell you who else thinks it’s her song,
but you’d better have earplugs handy
聞いてられなかったんだ
—Veronica.
ベロニカなんだけど
Oh, my goodness!
She’s in love with her own voice.
自分のこと うまいと思ってるんだよ
Ever sit near her at the hall?
集会でも歌手みたいに いつも
自分が一番って感じで歌ってるよね
It’s like she’s the only one that can sing.
And she’s such a diva.
それを聞いて思った
My first thought:
‘Oh, no! Here we go again!
「ああ まただわ 同じ展開」
I’ve seen this movie before.’
You don’t think she’s showing off?
やり過ぎだと思いません？
Is this just about Haley?
ヘイリーが悪いってこと？
It seems it’s all about Haley.
私はそう思ったんですけど
ちょっとねたんでるところない？
Is there just a little bit of envy in there?
I’ve lived it.
あんなことはもう・・・
If it’s a case of her being more careful
how she comes across,
もし限度を超えているっていうことなら
話は別だけどね
that’s another matter.
何かアドバイスくれた？
What did she suggest?
That I should tell her
that she needs to stop.
「やめるように言った方がいい」って
言われた
Can you believe that?
あれどうなのかな？開拓者だったら
模範にならないといけないのに
Especially as a pioneer,
what kind of example is she setting?
問題って 雪だるまみたいに
どんどん大きくなる
How quickly it snowballs out of control!
そういうことじゃなくって
That’s not what I am saying at all.
You are such . . .
そういうとこ あるよね
ほんと信じらんない
Wow! I can’t believe you.
さみしいからって
ほかにすることないんですか？
Are you that lonely
that you’ve got nothing better to do?
Haley!
ヘイリー
How difficult it can be to unravel!
こじれた関係を戻すって 難しい
ごめんなさい
I’m sorry.
I shouldn’t have judged you so harshly.
厳しく見過ぎてた
そんなふうに見るべきじゃなかった
I shouldn’t have judged you at all.
許すことはエホバに倣うチャンスになる
A chance to forgive
is a chance to imitate Jehovah.
自分が許してもらいたいと
思った時のこと 思い出してみて
Think back to a time
when you wanted forgiveness.
誰か
Has anyone ever tried talking to her
about her singing?
ベロニカに言ってあげたことある？
You know what I love about Veronica?
私がベロニカの好きなところはね
She’s probably the most hospitable person
I know.
ほんとによく人をもてなすところ
It’s always open house at her place.
いつもいろんな人を家に呼んでて
それに料理がうまいの
And can she cook!
Have you tried her curry?
カレー食べたことある？
食べたことない
I haven’t tried it yet.
Yeah, it’s so good.
ええ おいしいよ
すごいおいしい
It’s so good.
I really look forward to that.
え 食べてみたい
本当においしい
へえ 聞いてみよう
It’s really good.
OK, I’ll ask her.
うん 聞いてみたらいいよ
She does these curry nights.
よくカレー作ってみんなを招待してるよ
Oh, you’re going to love it.
絶対気に入るよ
We should use our gift of speech
ぜひ 他の人の励みになり 神の賛美に
つながるようなことを言いましょう
to honor God and to benefit others.
And if somebody gets angry at us,
もし誰かが腹を立てていても
私たちが穏やかに話すなら
our mild reply can diffuse the situation.
だんだん落ち着いてくるでしょう
As Proverbs 15:1 says:
格言 15:1にはこう書かれています
“A mild answer turns away rage,
「穏やかな答えは激しい怒りを静め
but a harsh word stirs up anger.”
きつい言葉は怒りをあおる」
We can also use our gift of speech
良い言葉を話して 人を慰めたり
励ましたりすることも大切です
to console and encourage others.
テサロニケ第一 5:11, 14には
こう述べられています
First Thessalonians 5:11, 14 states:
“Therefore, keep encouraging one another
and building one another up,
「それで すでにしている通り
これからも励まし合い
力づけ合ってください ⋯⋯
“just as you are in fact doing. . . .
兄弟たち さらに勧めます
“On the other hand, we urge you, brothers,
秩序を無視する人に警告を与え
“to warn the disorderly, speak consolingly
気落ちしている人に慰めの言葉を掛け
“to those who are depressed,
弱い人を支え 誰に対しても
辛抱強くあってください」
support the weak, be patient toward all.”
エホバに忠実に仕えている人でも
Yes, even faithful servants of Jehovah
may at times struggle with depression.
時に気落ちしてしまうことがあります
どうすれば助けになれるでしょうか
How can we help such ones?
Offer specific, genuine commendation
誠実に褒めて エホバがその人のことを
大切に思っていることを
to help them see their own value
in Jehovah’s eyes.
思い起こさせてあげましょう
Share with them the powerful words
of Bible texts
励みになる聖句を一緒に読んで
「心が傷ついた人」や
「打ちのめされた人」を
showing that Jehovah
truly cares about and loves those
エホバが深く愛して気遣っていることを
話し合いましょう
who “are broken at heart”
and “crushed in spirit.”
We can also use the power of our tongue
ほかにも 励ましを大いに必要として
いるどんな人たちがいるでしょうか
to provide much needed encouragement
to others.
Has a fellow believer lost
a loved one in death?
家族を亡くした仲間が
いるかもしれません
Sympathetic words
expressing our care and concern
親身になって
気遣いが伝わる言葉を掛けるなら
can comfort a grieving heart.
きっと慰めることができるでしょう
Is an elderly brother or sister
feeling unneeded?
寂しく感じている
年配の兄弟姉妹がいますか
A thoughtful tongue can reassure older ones
その人たちのことを尊敬していて
とても大切に思っていることを
伝えてあげましょう
that they are valued and appreciated.
Is someone struggling with a chronic illness?
病気で苦しんでいる仲間が
いるでしょうか
Kind words shared on the phone or in person
電話をかけたり直接訪ねたりして
思いやりのこもった言葉を掛けるなら
can do much to lift the spirits
of one who is sick.
元気づけることができるでしょう
How pleased our Creator must be
私たちがいつも「励ましの言葉」を
述べるように心掛けるなら
when we use the power of speech
to utter sayings
エホバはとても喜んでくださるに
違いありません
that are “good for building up”!
We may not be able to fix their problems,
落ち込んでいる人の問題を
解決してあげられないとしても
but we can let them know that we love them
その人のことを愛して
気遣っていることを伝えましょう
and we care about them.
一緒に時間を過ごして
じっくり話し合えるかもしれません
For example, you can arrange
to spend time with him or her.
Additionally, we can use God’s Word
励ます時に聖書を使うことは
とても大切です
to strengthen them.
Or you may notice
that someone in the congregation
会衆に元気がない人や
落ち込んでいる人がいたら
is discouraged or depressed.
どのようにできるでしょうか
You could read an encouraging Bible verse
励みになる聖句を読んで
一緒に祈ってあげられるかもしれません
and even offer to say a prayer.
Reassure such ones
会衆の兄弟姉妹たちから愛されている
と感じてもらえるようにしましょう
that their brothers and sisters
in the congregation love them.
And speak in a way that shows
自分の言葉が心からのものであることが
伝わるような話し方をしましょう
that you really mean and believe
what you say.
このシンポジウムを通して
This symposium has given each one of us
大事なことをたくさん
考えることができましたね
much to think about, has it not?
平和を追い求めるのは簡単ではない
場合も少なくありません
We have been reminded
that seeking peace is not always easy.
We have also learned
that the pursuit of peace
努力する必要がありますが
そうする価値は確かにあります
requires effort.
引き続き「平和を願い
追い求め［る］」ために
In what specific ways are you resolved
to “seek peace and pursue it”
具体的にどんな努力を
払いたいと思いましたか
in the days ahead?
May we all continue to pursue peace
ぜひ次の事柄を心掛けていきましょう
(1) by not quickly taking offense,
(1) すぐに腹を
立てないようにすること
(2) by apologizing,
(2) 進んで謝ること
(3) by forgiving freely,
(3) 気持ちよく許すこと
and (4) by using our gift of speech wisely
そして (4) 他の人を励ましたり
慰めたりできるように
to encourage and comfort others.
よく考えて話すことです
And may Jehovah, “the God of peace,”
「平和の神」であるエホバが
皆さんの努力を
豊かに祝福してくださいますように
bless you abundantly for doing so!
ありがとうございました
私たちの味わっている平和が
Thank you, brothers, for reminding us
that the peace we enjoy
does not happen by chance.
当たり前のものではないことを
思い起こせました
It requires continuous effort on our part,
それには私たちの努力が必要です
but we can succeed with Jehovah’s help.
でもエホバの助けがあれば
うまくいきます
We have now come
to the concluding talk of this session.
いよいよ次は 今日最後の話です
真のクリスチャンは さまざまな背景や
文化の人たちから成っています
True Christians come from a variety
of backgrounds and cultures.
Individual consciences differ.
それぞれ異なる良心を持っています
How can we remain united
どうすればそうした違いがあっても
一致していられるでしょうか
despite these differences?
Please give your attention
to Brother David Splane,
統治体の成員である
デービッド・スプレーン兄弟が
してくださる
a member of the Governing Body,
次の話に耳を傾けましょう
as he delivers the talk entitled
“Safeguard Our ‘Uniting Bond of Peace’!”
主題は「『平和という絆』を守る」です
When we think of unity,
一致と言えば 詩編 133:1の
言葉が思い浮かぶでしょう
the words of Psalm 133:1 may come to mind.
Let’s read them.
読みましょう
画面に聖句は出ないので
Now, the words
aren’t going to be on the screen,
どうぞ聖書を開いてご覧ください
so let’s look them up in the Bible.
I’ll give you a moment.
詩編 133:1です
That’s Psalm 133
and verse 1.
開けましたか こうあります
It says: “Look!
「兄弟たちが一致して共に住むのは
“How good and how pleasant it is
何と素晴らしいことだろう
for brothers to dwell together in unity!”
何と心地よいことだろう」
Well, we certainly agree
with these words of David.
このダビデの言葉に皆さんも
同意されるでしょう
Now, speaking of David,
he knew the value of unity.
ダビデは一致の大切さを知っていました
And we may remember
that he didn’t always get
でも ダビデの周りでいつも一致が
見られたわけではありません
to experience it in his own life.
The beginning and the end
of his reign were marked by civil war
治世の最初と最後には内戦が起きました
—the very opposite of unity.
一致とは程遠い状態です
But you’d think it would have been easy
イスラエル人が一致しなかったのは
不思議だと思うかもしれません
for the Israelites to remain united.
After all, they came from the same roots;
みんなルーツは同じで
they were all children of Abraham;
全員アブラハムの子孫でした
they spoke a common language—Hebrew;
ヘブライ語という同じ言語を話し
and they came
from a similar social background.
社会的な背景も大きな差は
ありませんでした
Their ancestors had all been slaves in Egypt.
祖先は皆 エジプトの奴隷でした
So there was no basis
for anybody to brag about his heritage.
それで血筋を誇れるような人は
誰もいませんでした
Still, the Israelites
found reasons to hate one another.
それでもイスラエル人は
憎み合う理由を見つけました
最初の王はベニヤミン族の人で
Israel’s first king was from Benjamin.
Its second king was from Judah.
2番目の王はユダ族の人でした
That was reason enough
to start a war in Israel.
それが理由で イスラエルで
内戦が起きてしまいました
Let’s fast-forward now to the first century.
では 1世紀に目を移しましょう
Unity is so important
that it was on Jesus’ mind
一致はとても重要なので イエスは
最後の晩にそのことを考えていました
on the night before he died.
それでイエスは 天の父と
自分が「一つであるように
You remember that he prayed to his Father
that his disciples ‘might be one
just as he and the Father are one.’
［弟子たち］も一つに
なる」ようにと祈りました
Now, that could have been a challenge.
一つになるには努力が要りました
Why do we say that?
なぜでしょうか
From a human standpoint,
人間的に見れば イエスの弟子たちが
一致する理由はありませんでした
there was no reason
for Jesus’ disciples to be united.
Unlike the Israelites,
イスラエル人のように共通の先祖から
出ていたわけではありません
they did not have a common ancestor,
they did not have a common mother tongue,
同じ言語を話していたわけではなく
しかも社会的な背景もさまざまでした
and they came
from a variety of social backgrounds.
Think of it: The first Christians
were Jews or Jewish proselytes.
1世紀 最初のクリスチャンは
ユダヤ人とユダヤ教への改宗者でした
Growing up, they were taught
that Gentiles were unclean,
異国人は汚れていると教えられて育ち
異国人の家に入るのはもちろん
and they wouldn’t even
enter the home of a Gentile,
異国人への伝道もしませんでした
let alone preach to one.
異国人のクリスチャンは
As for Gentile Christians,
they came “from every nation under heaven.”
「世界のあらゆる国から」来ていました
Most of them knew nothing
of the Hebrew language
そのほとんどはヘブライ語も
ヘブライ語聖書も知らず
or the Hebrew Scriptures.
偽の神々を崇拝していました
They’d worshipped false gods.
Some had been highly educated at Athens,
中には アテネやアレクサンドリア
といった学問の中心地で
Alexandria, or some other
center of worldly wisdom.
高等教育を受けた人たちもいました
Others had little formal education.
また あまり教育のない人もいました
Yet, when they accepted the truth,
それが真理を受け入れると
Christians became united
and at peace with one another.
クリスチャンは一致して
平和な関係になりました
The apostle Paul wanted to help them
使徒パウロは平和という絆を
守るよう助けたいと思いました
to safeguard that bond of peace.
それが今日この話の
テーマになっています
Now, that’s the theme
of our discussion this morning.
And we’re going to look at his words
エフェソス 4:3-6にある
言葉を見ましょう
recorded at Ephesians 4:3-6,
パウロがそこで使っている1つの
表現に注目しながら読みましょう
and we’re going
to focus in on a particular expression
in these verses.
どうぞエフェソス 4:3-6を
お開きください
This is Ephesians chapter 4.
I’ll give you a moment.
Ephesians chapter 4
開けましたか
and we’re going to read verses 3-6.
3-6節です
Now, Paul is interested in unity here,
パウロはここで一致に注目しています
その点をどのように強調しているか
見てみましょう
so let’s see how he frames his discussion.
He says: “Earnestly endeavoring
パウロはこう言っています
「平和という絆で結ばれ
“[so an effort is involved,
earnestly endeavoring]
聖なる力による一致を保つよう
“to maintain the oneness of the spirit
真剣に努力してください
“in the uniting bond of peace.
［真剣な努力が求められています］
体は1つ 聖なる力は1つです
“One body there is, and one spirit,
皆さんが招かれて
差し伸べられた希望も1つです
“just as you were called
to the one hope of your calling;
［さらに強調していきます］
“[and then he emphasizes]
one Lord, one faith,
主はひとり 信仰は1つ
バプテスマは1つです
“one baptism; one God
全ての人の父である神はひとりであり」
and Father of all.”
Now, let’s go back to verse 3
and look at the expression
3節を見ると 「平和という絆」
という表現があります
“the uniting bond of peace.”
この話の「『平和という絆』を守る」
という主題はここから取られています
So our discussion
is “Safeguard Our ‘Uniting Bond of Peace’!”
スタディー版聖書の注釈には
Now, the Study Bible{
この表現について
興味深い説明があり
It tells us that the word
translated “uniting bond”
ここで使われているギリシャ語は
can also be translated “ligament”
—ligament.
「靱帯」とも訳せます
実際 ほかの聖句では
And it is translated
“ligament” in other verses.
「靱帯」と訳されています
Now, we know what a ligament is.
ご存じのように 靱帯とは
It’s a band of strong tissue
that holds our bones together.
骨と骨を結び付ける強い組織です
So when we talk
about the uniting bond of peace,
ですから 平和という絆
という表現からすると
we mean that peace is the ligament.
平和は靱帯のように神の民を
しっかり結び合わせています
It’s the tissue
that holds God’s people together.
That was true in the first century
and is true today.
1世紀もそうでしたし 今日もそうです
Like the early Christians,
初期クリスチャンのように
we come from different backgrounds;
私たちも背景はさまざまで
いろいろな言語を話します
we speak different languages.
Yet, Jehovah has shown us
how to remain united
でも 平和と一致を保つ
方法を学んでいます
and at peace.
エホバからです
Now, let’s explain
what we mean by being united.
では 一致しているとは
どういうことかを考えましょう
To be united doesn’t mean
that we all have to like the same things
一致とは 皆が同じ好みや見方を
or we all have
to think the same on every subject.
持たなければならない
ということではありません
There’s room
for a variety of tastes and opinions.
いろいろな意見や好みを
持つことができます
There’s variety on this convention program.
この大会にも多様性が見られます
We don’t all wear the same style of suit
皆が同じスタイルのスーツや
同じ色のネクタイをしてはいません
or have the same color of tie.
What about you?
皆さんはどんな色が好きですか
What’s your favorite color?
your favorite food?
どんな食べ物
どんなペットが好きですか
your favorite pet?
In Jehovah’s organization,
there are dog lovers and cat lovers.
エホバの組織には 犬好きの人も
猫好きの人もいて
どんな種類の犬や猫が好きかも違います
And not everyone
likes the same breed of dog or cat.
Have you ever visited someone
誰かの家に行ってペットを見せられて
who has a pet
that he thinks is just adorable?
「かわいいでしょう」と
言われたことがありますか
You take one look at the animal,
でも 一目見て 「このペットを
かわいいと思う人なんか
and you wonder
how anyone could love a face like that.
いるんだろうか」と思います
Yet, he does.
いるんです 好みの違いです
People are different,
and their pets are grateful for that.
そのペットは幸せですね
今 私たちの間に見られる多様性は
新しい世界でも続きます
The variety we find among God’s people today
will continue on into the new world.
エホバは違いを楽しむ神です
Jehovah loves variety.
How many colors are there?
色は何色ありますか
How many species of plants,
birds, and animals are there?
植物 鳥 動物の種類はどれほどですか
Among God’s creation,
we find the simple and the complex,
創造物には シンプルなもの
複雑なもの
地味なもの 派手なもの
the plain and the fancy,
the sweet and the sour,
甘いもの 辛いもの
the rough and the smooth.
いろいろあります
There’s great variety among people.
人間も多種多様です
Even in the new world,
新しい世界で 完全な人も
perfect humans won’t have
the same personality,
同じ性格 才能 能力を
持つわけではありません
talents, and abilities.
You’ve always wanted to play the violin?
バイオリンを弾きたいと思っていますか
Don’t think that when you’re perfect,
完全になったらバイオリンを手にして
すぐに弾けるとは思わないでください
you’ll just be able
to pick up a violin and play.
And there’s no guarantee
you’ll be able to play in our orchestra.
私たちのオーケストラに加われる
保証はありません
Now, one way to maintain unity
一致を保つ1つの方法は
is to respect the conscience of others.
ほかの人の良心を尊重することです
This is very important
これはとても大事なことです
because very often when unity is disturbed,
兄弟姉妹が自分で決定できるという
事実を認めないことが原因で
it’s because we don’t respect
the ability of other brothers and sisters
一致できなくなるということが
よくあるからです
to decide things for themselves.
では 良心とは何でしょうか
Now, what do we mean by the conscience?
一言で言うと 良心とは
Let’s be simple.
It’s the faculty
善悪を判断するのに役立つ機能です
that helps us determine right from wrong.
I’m going to repeat that.
繰り返します 良心とは善悪を
判断する機能と言えます
The conscience is the faculty
to determine right from wrong.
Now, let’s consider
how our upbringing and our culture
善悪に対する私たちの見方に
育ちや文化がどのように
影響するかを考えてみましょう
can help shape
our personal view of right and wrong.
In some cultures, there are large families.
ある文化では大家族が普通で
食事の時にはみんな大声で
よくしゃべり 本当ににぎやかです
Conversation around the dinner table is loud.
You can hardly hear yourself think.
The children tease one another
子供同士でからかったり
and don’t hesitate
to ask each other personal questions.
どんなことでも 遠慮なく
話したり尋ねたりします
The girls borrow each other’s clothes,
娘たちは互いの服を借り
時には勝手にそうします
sometimes without asking.
Some people would say that’s wrong,
それは良くないと思いますか
but the girls see nothing wrong with it,
でも 娘たちも親たちも
全く気にしていません
and neither do their parents.
In other cultures, family members
are polite and courteous,
別の文化では家庭の中でも
礼儀が重んじられます
but they don’t talk much
about their plans or their feelings.
そして 自分の考えや気持ちを
あまり話しません
The parents don’t often talk about their past
プライバシーを大事にするので
親は昔のことをほとんど話しません
because they value their privacy.
Now, some who were raised that way
そのような環境で育った人は
tend to be rather strict
with themselves and others.
自分にも人にも
厳しくなることがあります
They have definite views of right and wrong.
いい悪いがはっきりしているのです
勝手に服を借りたりしたら
Borrow their clothes without asking
「それは盗みだ 長老に報告する」
と言うでしょう
and they’ll say: “That’s stealing.
I’m calling the elders.”
There are no gray areas with them.
その人たちにとって
グレーゾーンはありません
Now, there are lots of exceptions,
例外もたくさんあり ある文化の人が
皆同じというわけではありませんが
and we’re not saying that everyone
in a certain culture fits the bill.
要点は伝わったと思います
But you get the idea.
Now, what do you suppose happens
では 例えばある伝道者が
when a publisher from one culture
ある文化圏の会衆から
moves into a congregation
where the other culture predominates?
別の文化圏の会衆に
移動したとしましょう
If he doesn’t adjust
his way of viewing others,
自分の見方を調整しなければ
he’ll be miserable.
惨めなことになります
Is one way right and the other wrong?
文化に優劣があるのでしょうか
No.
いいえ どちらの文化の人も
相手から学べます
Members of both cultures
could learn from one another.
Speaking of culture, we might ask ourselves,
この点についてこう自問できます
‘How do I feel about brothers and sisters
「自分とはかなり違う
文化の兄弟姉妹について
who come from cultures
that are very different from my own?’
どう感じているだろうか」
They may speak with an accent.
なまりがあったり
Their style of dress may be different.
服装が違ったりするかもしれません
Their manners and food
may not be what we’re used to.
食べる物やマナーも違うことがあります
Suppose that an elder
is younger than we are
もし長老が自分より年下だったら
or from a different race.
人種が違ったら 助言を受け入れますか
Will we accept his counsel?
Will we ask him for counsel?
その長老に助言を求めるでしょうか
Or will we look for an elder who’s older
それとも 自分より年上で
背景がよく似た長老の所に行きますか
and from a similar background?
Will we celebrate our differences,
違いを楽しむでしょうか
それとも その違いによって
一致を乱されてしまうでしょうか
or will we allow them to disturb our unity?
So that’s one thing.
これが1つ目です
But let’s talk about our personal history.
別の点として 自分が
経験してきたことや
Our personal history
can also affect our view of right and wrong.
生い立ちが善悪に対する見方に
影響することがあります
Some grew up in a household
where alcohol was a problem.
例えば アルコールの問題を抱えた
家庭で育った人たちがいます
Home was not a happy place.
家庭にいい思い出はなく
大人になってから
And as adults, they stay
as far away from alcohol as they can,
できるだけアルコールに
関わらないようにしています
and they take a dim view
of anyone who uses it,
適度ではあってもアルコールを
飲む人のことを
even in moderation.
あまり良く思っていません
その人にとって飲酒は
とにかく悪いことです
To them, it’s just plain wrong to drink.
Others have only good memories
of their childhood home.
子供時代に良い思い出しか
ない人もいます
At supper time,
there was always wine on the table,
夕食ではテーブルに
いつもワインがあって
誰も飲み過ぎたりはしませんでした
but nobody ever abused it.
A person who left behind an immoral lifestyle
以前に不道徳な生活をしていた人は
might be extremely sensitive
about choices of clothing.
服装のことが非常に気になって
しまう場合があります
He may be troubled by a clothing style
ほかのクリスチャンが全く
問題ないと思う服装に
that other brothers and sisters
find totally acceptable.
心を乱されてしまうかもしれません
If they’re not careful,
自分に厳しい人は注意していないと
those who tend to be strict with themselves
自分の良心をほかの人に
押し付けてしまいかねません
could impose their conscience on others.
Now let’s consider a familiar scenario.
では ありがちな場面を
考えてみましょう
Four publishers
are working rural territory in a car group.
4人の伝道者が車で
田舎の区域を奉仕しています
Now, each home is separated from the next
家と家がお互いに何キロも
離れているような区域です
by many miles or kilometers.
At the first call, the driver
運転手の姉妹ともう1人が
最初の家を訪問し
and her companion get out
and the other sisters stay in the car.
ほかの2人は車に残ります
They have no choice.
There’s no place to go.
行く所はありません
Now, the householder has many questions,
家の人がたくさん質問をして
and a Bible study has started.
聖書レッスンが始まります
It’s noon when the two publishers
return to the car
2人が喜びにあふれて車に戻ったのは
—all smiles.
お昼でした
You know what’s coming next, don’t you?
どうなるか分かりますね
One of the sisters in the back seat says,
車にいた姉妹の1人が言います
「ねえ 私たち2人とも
時間が入らなかったわ」
“Well, the two of us
can’t count any time this morning.”
What’s she done?
姉妹は 「2人とも」と言って
She’s spoken for herself
and for her companion.
そのつもりはなかったかもしれませんが
And unintentionally, she’s imposed
her own conscience on her friend.
自分の良心をもう1人の姉妹に
押し付けています
Now, if she doesn’t want
to count any time, that’s her business.
姉妹がそれを奉仕時間に
数えなかったのは 姉妹の決定です
It would be best
if she kept her business to herself.
人を巻き込まない方が良かったでしょう
外国に旅行に行った時
If you’ve ever visited a foreign country
and gone on a guided tour,
ガイド付きのツアーに参加すると
probably one of the things
the tour guide wanted to show you
教会内部の見学が
そのコースの一部に
含まれていることがよくあります
was the architecture inside a church.
Now, some brothers
have no problem entering a church
ツアーの一部であれば 教会に入るのは
博物館に行くのと同じで
if it’s part of a tour because to them
it’s no different from visiting a museum.
何の抵抗もないという兄弟もいます
Others who were
strong supporters of false religion
でも 間違った宗教の信者だった
ある兄弟は
couldn’t enter a church for any reason,
どんな理由でも教会には入りません
not even to attend a wedding or a funeral.
結婚式の時や葬式の時もです
その兄弟にとって それは
とにかく悪いことなのです
To them, it’s just plain wrong.
Consciences can differ in this respect,
良心はそれぞれ異なるので
それを認めて尊重しなければなりません
and we have to respect that;
we have to acknowledge that.
この点は後ほどさらに考えます
And we’re going to expand
on that idea in a moment.
Well, we’ve hardly scratched the surface
このように エホバの組織の中に
いろいろな個性やさまざまな
見方があることについては
when it comes to describing
the variety of personalities
and viewpoints in Jehovah’s organization.
挙げていけば切りがありません
So here’s the question:
それで考えたいのは
How can we maintain our unity?
どうすれば一致を保てるか
ということです
パウロは何と言いましたか
Remember what Paul said?
“Earnestly endeavoring to maintain”
完全な一致の絆を保つよう
—maintain this perfect bond of unity.
「保つよう真剣に努力してください」
It means that we have to put forth effort
そうです 一致を保つために
努力しなければなりません
to maintain that unity.
Well, first of all,
it’ll help a lot to get well-acquainted
まず 自分とは考え方の違う
兄弟姉妹をよく知るようにしましょう
with brothers and sisters
who think differently from us.
Get to know their background.
背景を知ってください
That’ll help you not to overreact
あなたの受け入れにくい決定を
その兄弟がするとしても
when they take a position
that you don’t agree with.
過剰に反応しないで済みます
It’ll help us not to judge them.
批判しないで済みます
Now, Paul wrote very plainly on that subject
ローマ 14:4で
パウロはその点について
とても率直に述べています
in the words found at Romans 14:4
—simple statement but very powerful.
シンプルですが 説得力があります
Let’s check it out together
at Romans chapter 14
どうぞローマ 14:4を
お開きください
(I’ll give you a moment)
and verse 4.
お読みします
Paul writes: “Who are you
「他人の召し使いを批判するとは
あなたは何者なのですか
“to judge the servant of another?
その人が立つのも倒れるのも
“To his own master he stands or falls.
その人と主人との間でのことなのです
“Indeed, he will be made to stand,
実際 その人は立つようにされます
for Jehovah can make him stand.”
エホバはその人を立たせることが
できるからです」
Now let’s go back
and look at that first sentence again:
もう一度 最初の一文をご覧ください
“Who are you to judge
「他人の召し使いを批判するとは
the servant of another?”
あなたは何者なのですか」
We know what a judge does.
私たちは批判しません
He declares someone guilty or not guilty.
裁判官のように有罪無罪を
決めたりしません
That’s not our job.
裁くのは私たちではなくエホバです
Jehovah is the Judge.
一人一人が自分の考え方や
良心を向上させようとするなら
If each of us concentrates
on his own thinking and his own conscience,
the peace and unity
of the congregation will be preserved.
会衆の平和と一致が守られます
私たちは何が良くて何が
良くないかを決める時
Well, we all want to be balanced
when we determine
what is right and what is wrong.
バランスを取りたいと思います
We want to have a balanced view of things
—a good conscience.
バランスの取れた見方
健全な良心を持ちたいと思います
So how can we be balanced
あることが良いか悪いかを判断する時
when determining
whether something is right or wrong?
どうすればバランスを取れますか
Now, in some cases, it’s easy;
the Bible tells us.
聖書にはっきり書かれている
場合は簡単ですが
But in other cases, there’s no clear answer.
そうでない場合もあります
Let’s consider a scenario
we touched on earlier
先ほど取り上げた教会に入るか
という例を考えましょう
—the matter of entering a church.
Now, that may not be
a problem where you live,
皆さんの地域では問題に
ならないかもしれませんが
but in some places, it’s a real issue.
場所によってはよくある問題です
And remember, these talks
are for our worldwide brotherhood.
この大会の話は世界中の兄弟たちに
向けられたものなので
So we’re going to consider a subject
多くの兄弟姉妹が実際に直面する点を
取り上げたいと思います
that will be a real problem
for many to overcome,
and we hope that they will benefit from it.
役に立つことを願っています
こんな場面です
So here’s the scenario:
Two different sisters are married
to men who are not in the truth.
未信者の夫を持つ姉妹が
2人いるとします
Now, in both cases,
the husband’s mother has died.
2人とも夫の母親が亡くなりました
The funeral will be in a church.
葬式は教会で行われます
One sister decides to go;
1人は行くことにしますが
the other decides against it.
もう1人は行かないことにします
The sister who decides to attend
出席すると決めた姉妹は
その教会では聖職者が話を
するだけだということを考慮しました
has considered that in that church,
there will just be a talk by a clergyman.
There will be no congregation singing,
賛美歌や祈り その他の
宗教儀式は行われません
congregation prayers, or religious gestures.
She was never very religious anyway,
姉妹は教会の信者ではなかったので
so none of that would mean anything to her.
そういうことにそもそも
特別な意味を感じません
And her husband and his family will be happy
夫も家族も 姉妹が静かに
座っているだけで満足します
if she just sits quietly until it’s over.
Now, the second sister
has a different set of circumstances.
もう1人の姉妹の状況は異なります
The service in that church
involves participation by the congregation.
教会での葬式には出席者が
参加する部分があります
She used to be
an active member of that church,
姉妹はその教会の信者でした
何か後悔するようなことをして
しまわないか心配しています
and she’s afraid
she’ll do something she’ll regret.
Her husband’s family
get very emotional at funerals,
夫の家族は葬式の時に
とても感情的になるので
and they’re likely to make a scene
if she doesn’t participate.
姉妹が葬式で何もしないと
騒ぎになりそうです
So she respectfully tells her husband
that her attendance
それで姉妹は夫に 自分が出席すると
困らせることになりかねないと
could cause him embarrassment
and declines to attend.
敬意を込めて伝え
出席しないことにします
You can see that each situation is different.
それぞれの状況は異なるということです
Now we’re going to discuss four questions
that we might ask ourselves
これから難しい決定をしなければ
ならない時に考慮するとよい
when we’re called upon
to make any difficult decision.
4つの質問を取り上げていきます
質問は2回言いますね
And I will repeat the question
because if you’re taking notes,
ノートを取っている方は
その点だけでも
you may want to at least
write the question down.
書き留めたいと思われるでしょう
These are very, very good questions
that we can ask ourselves
難しい決定をする前に自問するとよい
とても役立つ質問です
before we make a difficult decision.
行きますよ 1つ目は
Are you ready?
Here’s number one:
何がエホバに喜ばれるかです
What will make Jehovah happy?
I’ll repeat that.
繰り返します 何がエホバに
喜ばれるかです
What will make Jehovah happy?
And that should be our main concern,
to please Jehovah.
そのことを私たちは
一番気に掛けています
Well, how do we know
what will make Jehovah happy?
では 何をすればいいでしょうか
We identify the Bible principles
that have a bearing on the situation.
関係する聖書の原則を見極めることです
One way we can do that
そのために「索引」や
「リサーチガイド」を活用できます
is by checking the Index{
未信者の夫を持つ姉妹が
What are some Scriptural principles
教会での葬式に出席するかを
決める時に考慮できる
a sister who’s married to an unbeliever
might consider when deciding
whether to attend a funeral in a church?
どんな聖書の原則があるでしょうか
思い付きますか
Can you think of some?
ペテロ第一 3:1はどうでしょうか
What about 1 Peter 3:1?
“Wives, be in subjection to your husbands.”
「妻の皆さん 夫に従ってください」
夫がクリスチャンであってもなくても
Jehovah is pleased when
a Christian woman respects her husband,
妻が夫を敬う時
エホバは喜ばれます
whether he’s in the truth or not.
But a wife’s subjection is relative.
でも夫の権威は絶対的な
ものではありません
She’s dedicated to Jehovah,
妻が献身したのは夫ではなくエホバです
not to her husband.
She’s dedicated to Jehovah,
妻は夫ではなくエホバに献身しました
not to her husband.
So that’s 1 Peter 3:1.
1つの原則を考えました
What about Isaiah 52:11?
イザヤ 52:11はどうでしょうか
「汚れたものには一切触れるな！⋯⋯
“Touch nothing unclean! . . .
Keep yourselves clean.”
身を清く保て」
Under the Mosaic Law,
モーセの律法では
汚れたものに触れただけで
if someone so much as
touched something unclean,
汚れた人になりました
he became unclean.
Many brothers and sisters
would find it very hard to sit quietly
多くの兄弟姉妹は
聖職者が死者の状態について
偽りを語るのを聞いてはいられないと
感じることでしょう
while a clergyman told lies
about the condition of the dead.
To them, it would be
touching something unclean.
汚れたものに触れるような
ことだと思えるのです
Others might compare that
to a young person in school
一方 学校の先生が生命の起源について
sitting quietly while his teacher
tells lies about the origin of life.
偽りを語るのを聞いているのと
同じだと考える人もいます
If someone does decide
to attend a funeral in a church,
もし教会での葬式に出席するのであれば
he or she should be absolutely determined
どんな宗教儀式にも絶対に
加わったりはしないと
not to participate in any religious ritual,
固く決意しているべきです
whether singing hymns
or so much as saying “amen”
賛美歌を歌ったり 聖職者の祈りに
「アーメン」と言ったりはしません
to a prayer that the clergyman offers.
大切なのはエホバを喜ばせることです
Remember, the goal is to please Jehovah.
So the first point was,
それで1つ目の点は
What makes Jehovah happy?
何がエホバに喜ばれるかでした
Number two—number two:
2つ目に行きましょう
How might my choice affect others?
自分の選択が他の人に
どんな影響を与えるか
Have you got that?
書けましたか 自分の選択が
他の人にどんな影響を与えるかです
How might my choice
affect others?
We would never want to stumble anyone.
誰の信仰も妨げたくはありません
Even in a family matter,
家族のこと 教会での結婚式や
葬式に出席するなど
such as attending a wedding
or a funeral in a church
(which we may consider as a personal matter),
個人的と思えることでも
we need to weigh the effect our decision
自分の決定が他の人に
与えかねない影響を考えるべきです
could have on others.
It could affect them in one of two ways.
2通りの影響があり得ます
Now, the first is the obvious way.
1つは はっきりしています
In some areas, if a Witness
even entered a church,
地域によっては ある兄弟が
教会に入るだけで
兄弟姉妹はその兄弟への敬意を失います
his brothers and sisters
would lose respect for him.
But there’s a second way
the Witness could stumble someone.
人に影響を与える
もう1つの場合があります
He might be able to attend the funeral
and make no compromise.
その兄弟は葬式に出席しても
妥協しないかもしれません
But suppose a new brother decided
でも 新しい兄弟が家族の葬式で
それに倣おうとしたとします
to follow his example
when a family member died.
The new brother could give in
to family pressure
新しい兄弟は家族の圧力に負けて
and participate in idolatry.
偶像崇拝をしてしまいました
How tragic is that!
残念なことです
The apostle Paul never worshipped idols.
使徒パウロは偶像を崇拝しませんでした
So when meat that had been offered to an idol
went up for sale in a meat market,
偶像に何の意味もないことを
知っていたので
偶像に捧げられた肉が
市場で売られていたら
it probably didn’t bother
Paul’s conscience to buy it
それを買うことに良心のとがめを
感じなかったでしょう
because he knew that an idol is nothing.
But some of his brothers had worshipped
でもクリスチャンになる前に
まさにそうした偶像を崇拝していた
兄弟たちもいました
those very idols
before coming into the truth.
They could have felt guilty
about eating that meat.
その肉を食べることに罪の意識を
感じたかもしれません
To them, it would be
like having a communion meal with an idol.
偶像と食事をするような
ものだったのです
The feelings of his brothers
were important to Paul.
パウロは その兄弟たちの
気持ちを大切にし
He was willing to sacrifice his own rights
その兄弟たちのために自分の権利を
進んで犠牲にしました
for the sake of his brothers.
We’d never want to take the unloving view
私たちのしたことで気を
乱されている兄弟について
that if our brother
is stumbled by what we do,
「その兄弟の問題だ」と言うのは
愛のないことです
it’s too bad for him.
On the other hand,
一方で ほかの人がすることで
気を乱されてしまうことがよくあるなら
if we’re the type of person
who is often stumbled by what others do,
we need to ask Jehovah
to help us gain a more balanced viewpoint.
バランスの取れた見方を持てるよう
エホバに祈る必要があります
So far, we’ve discussed
the need to make Jehovah happy
ここまで エホバを喜ばせることと
兄弟たちの気持ちを
考えることをお話ししました
and to consider the feelings of our brothers.
What’s next?
次は3つ目
Number three: Have I asked for counsel?
助言を求めたかという点です
You got that?
書けましたか
助言を求めたかという点です
Have I asked for counsel?
Now, maybe the elders haven’t dealt
with the exact situation we’re facing,
長老たちは全く同じ状況を
扱ったことがなくても
いろいろな場合を知っています
but they know a lot of people.
They may know someone
who has dealt with the situation before
誰かがよく似た状況でどのように
対処したかを知っているかもしれません
and saw how he handled it.
Or they may know about the effect
the decision had on others.
その決定がほかの人に与えた
影響も知っていることでしょう
For example, they might know
how the congregation reacted
例えば 前回 誰かが教会での
結婚式や葬式に出席した時
the last time someone attended a wedding
会衆がどう反応したかといったことです
or a funeral in a church.
Another situation where brothers often ask
for the help of the elders
兄弟たちがよく長老の援助を
求める別の状況は
involves the use of blood fractions.
血液分画が関係する場合です
受け入れるべきですか
避けるべきですか
Should we accept them or not?
The Governing Body has refused
to impose its conscience on the brotherhood.
統治体は兄弟たちに良心を
押し付けたりはしません
私たちは 聖書が「血を避ける」ように
と言っていることを知っています
But what do we know?
We know that the Bible says
to “abstain . . . from blood.”
But as you divide it into fractions
でも 血を分画に分けていくと
and the fractions get tinier and tinier,
どんどん小さく小さくなっていきます
at what point does blood stop being blood?
では どの時点で血では
なくなるのでしょうか
Each one will have to decide that
for himself.
それは各自が決めなければなりません
Now, some might say,
「本当に小さな分画であれば
“Well, if it’s a really,
really tiny fraction,
受け入れることに抵抗はない」
と言う人もいれば
it doesn’t bother me to take it.”
「そんなことは関係ない
血から取ったものを
But others will say:
“It doesn’t matter to me.
自分は受け入れたくない」
と言う人もいます
If it’s from blood, I don’t want it.”
And their conscience
also has to be respected.
その人たちの良心も
尊重されなければなりません
Now let’s illustrate:
例えで考えましょう
Air is made up of nitrogen
空気の主要成分は
and oxygen,
窒素と酸素で
and together they make up 99 percent of air.
合わせて空気の99パーセントを
占めています
That leaves 1 percent.
残りは1パーセントです
The 1 percent is made up
of a variety of gases:
その1パーセントを構成する
いろいろな気体は
carbon dioxide, hydrogen, neon
二酸化炭素 水素 ネオン
といった微小成分です
—small fractions.
When it comes to small fractions,
微小分画について 長老たちは
elders need to be careful, though,
「私はどれも受け入れない」
などと言って
not to insert their personal opinion
into the discussion,
個人的な意見を持ち込まないように
注意する必要があります
such as by saying
“I wouldn’t take any of it.”
They should simply help the publisher
to reason on the basic principles
伝道者が基本的な原則を考えて
自分で決定できるよう助けるべきです
and let him make up his own mind.
So where are we?
ここまで考えたのは
エホバを喜ばせること
We make Jehovah happy.
We consider the feelings
of our brothers and sisters.
兄弟姉妹の気持ちを考えること
助言を求めることです
We ask for counsel.
Number four:
4つ目は 時間を取って
Did I take the time
—did I take the time—
時間を取って 決定する前に
祈ってよく考えることです
to meditate prayerfully
before making my decision?
時間を取って 決定する前に
祈ってよく考えることです
Did I take the time to meditate prayerfully
before making my decision?
Your goal is to make Jehovah happy.
目指すのはエホバを喜ばせることです
So you wouldn’t want
to make your decision hastily
急いで決定してから祝福を
求めるようなことはしたくありません
and then ask Jehovah to bless it.
We should ask Jehovah for guidance first
下した決定に祝福を求めるのではなく
rather than asking him to bless a decision
エホバの導きを求めてまず祈るべきです
we’ve already made.
Have you ever heard someone say,
あることについて「自分の良心は
痛まない」と誰かが言うのを聞いて
“That doesn’t bother my conscience”?
We might ask:
‘How did he come to that conclusion?
こう思うかもしれません
「どうしてそう考えたんだろうか
‘Did he follow the four steps
we just mentioned?
先ほどの4つのステップを
踏んだんだろうか
‘Did he do research to learn
what makes Jehovah happy?
何がエホバに喜ばれるかをよく調べ
‘Did he think
about how others might be affected?
ほかの人に与える影響を考え
‘Did he ask for counsel?
助言を求め 決定について
祈ってよく考えたんだろうか
‘And did he meditate prayerfully
on his decision?
Or is he just following his feelings?’
それとも自分の感覚に
従っただけだろうか」
Following your feelings isn’t the same
自分の感覚に従うのは
聖書に沿って整えられた良心に
従うのと同じではありません
as following a Bible-trained conscience.
I’m going to repeat that.
繰り返します 自分の感覚に従うのは
Following your feelings is not the same
聖書に沿って整えられた良心に
従うのと同じではありません
as following a Bible-trained conscience.
Our conscience needs to be trained
良心を聖書の原則に沿って
整えなければなりません
in harmony with Scriptural principles.
Now, Paul’s conscience
didn’t bother him a bit
パウロはクリスチャンを迫害していた時
良心の痛みを感じませんでした
when he was persecuting Christians.
エホバのためにしていると
思っていました
He thought he was doing Jehovah a favor.
But when he realized
how Jehovah felt about it,
でも エホバがどう感じているかを
知った時
he knew he had to change.
変化しようと思いました
We have to be sure that we’re really getting
Jehovah’s thinking on matters.
私たちはエホバの考えを本当に
つかんでいるか確かめるべきです
Remember Jeremiah 17:9
エレミヤ 17:9を
思い出してください
—simple expression but so true.
シンプルですが 本質を捉えています
Jeremiah chapter 17
エレミヤ 17:9
and verse 9 says:
“The heart is more treacherous
「心はほかのどんなものよりも
信用できず 必死になる
“than anything else and is desperate.
Who can know it?”
誰がこれを知り得るだろうか」
‘The heart is treacherous.’
「心は⋯⋯信用」できません
We might allow our emotions
to get the better of us.
感情に流されてしまうことがあり得ます
例えば 家族の1人が排斥された時
For example, when a family member
is disfellowshipped,
if the person is living outside the home,
その人が一緒に住んでいなければ
交友を制限します
we know that we should limit our association
to necessary family business.
家族の必要な事柄だけにです
Now, if the family was never very close,
that might not be a problem.
もともと行き来がそれほどなければ
問題にはならないでしょう
But suppose family ties are really strong;
でも家族の絆が本当に強い場合
that can be a challenge.
試練になり得ます
If we allow ourselves to be ruled by emotion
聖書の原則に従うのではなく
感情に左右されてしまうなら
rather than by Scriptural principles,
we could stretch the meaning
of necessary family business
家族の必要な事柄の意味を広げて
ほとんどの活動を含めて
しまうかもしれません
to include almost any activity.
The heart is treacherous.
心は信用できません
Asking ourselves
the four questions we just mentioned
先ほどの4つの点を自問するなら
can help us to make decisions
based on godly principles
ただ感情に任せた決定をするのではなく
rather than simply relying on our feelings.
神の原則に基づいて決定できます
Now let’s see how mature Christians
では 兄弟姉妹が原則を
どう当てはめているか
can apply these principles
and how the elders can help.
長老たちがどう援助できるかを
見てみましょう
The following video interviews
次のビデオでは 多くの文化で気を使う
are about weddings and funerals
結婚式や葬式の問題が扱われます
—a touchy subject
in many cultures, as you will see.
ご覧ください
日本において宗教儀式は
人生の節目節目で
In Japan,
religious rituals are associated
with each stage of life
また季節ごとに生活に根付いています
and with each season of the year.
エホバの証人として私たちは
As Jehovah’s Witnesses,
会衆の清さと一致を
保ちたいと願っています
we want to keep the cleanliness and unity
of the congregation.
この点で最もデリケートな
問題となり得る分野の1つは
In this regard,
one of the most delicate areas
やはり 一般的な葬式に出席するか
どうかという決定があります
is the decision on whether to attend
a non-Witness funeral or not.
葬式に関連してまず
考える必要があるのは
The first thing we must consider
regarding funerals is not to be involved
聖書が非とする
宗教儀式や崇拝行為には
in religious rituals and acts of worship
that are condemned by the Bible.
関わらないようにするということです
In harmony with the principle
コリント第二 6:14にある
原則に従って
at 2 Corinthians 6:14,
異教の崇拝行為からは
we need to keep completely separate
完全に離れる必要があります
from pagan acts of worship.
次に たとえ他の宗教の
崇拝行為に加わらないとしても
Next, even if we don’t participate
in the worship of other religions,
私たちの決定で
we need to consider if our decisions
could stumble someone in the congregation.
会衆の誰かをつまずかせてしまう
ことがないか という点を考えます
ルカ 17:2の聖書の
原則を考えるときに
When we consider the Bible principle
at Luke 17:2,
私たちの決定で会衆の誰かの信仰を
we do not want our decisions to hinder
the faith of someone in the congregation.
妨げてしまうということが
ないようにしたいと思います
3つ目に考えることができるのは
The third point to think about
is our conscience.
自分の良心の問題です
ガラテア 6:5の
We need to seriously think
about the Bible principle
人はそれぞれ自分の荷を
負うのですという
at Galatians 6:5, where it says
この聖書の原則を真剣に
考えなければなりません
that each must “carry his own load.”
この聖書の原則は
This Bible principle also applies
when elders want to support others.
長老たちが他の人を援助するときにも
当てはまります
もちろん会衆の奉仕者たちが
葬式に関連して
Of course, those in the congregation
can ask the elders for support
長老たちに援助を求めるのは
良いことです
in issues related to funerals.
それでも長老たちは
自分の良心上の決定を
However, in matters of conscience,
elders cannot force decisions on others.
他の人に押し付けることはできません
それで一般的な葬式に
出席することに関して
So it would be wrong to make
some kind of rule regarding attending
一律のルールを作ることは
ふさわしくありません
non-Witness funerals.
一人一人が聖書の原則に基づいて
決定できるようになるなら
If each person can make
decisions based on Bible principles,
we can have a truly peaceful
それぞれの異なる状況を尊重して
and free atmosphere
where each individual’s
本当に平和で自由な雰囲気になります
differing situation is respected.
それは本当の意味での
会衆の一致に貢献します
This would really contribute
to the unity of the congregation.
そして みんながエホバの前で
清い良心を保って
And all can maintain a clean conscience
幸福のうちに奉仕することが
できるようになります
and serve happily before Jehovah.
In my culture,
私はナミビアのオシワンボ族の出身です
specifically the Namibian Oshiwambo
culture,
like in many African cultures,
アフリカでは結婚式の祝い事の中に
there are many spiritistic customs
related to weddings
心霊術に関係したものが
たくさんあります
that are included in wedding celebrations.
Unfortunately, my family is not in the truth.
私の家族はエホバの証人ではありません
So obviously, for Ben and I,
そのことが気掛かりでした
that was one of the main concerns.
私たちはエホバを喜ばせたい
They don’t understand our worship of Jehovah,
and they don’t understand
that we apply Bible principles
しきたりではなく聖書の原則に
従いたい と思っていました
and not the traditions of men.
We got engaged before the pandemic,
パンデミック前に婚約し
but obviously, now that our wedding
was to be over videoconferencing,
結婚式はビデオ会議で
することになりました
it meant that we didn’t have control
over many things.
でも どうなるかが心配でした
We tried to imagine situations
誰かの信仰を妨げたり
that could stumble our brothers or disrupt
一致を壊したりすることに
ならないか 考えました
the unity in the congregation.
We had to, in advance,
関係する聖書の原則について
前もって考えました
think of Bible principles
that would apply in our case,
but particularly what we also found helpful
was speaking to a mature elder.
経験ある長老に
相談したのも良かったです
格言 14:15を見せてくれました
He gave us a principle at Proverbs 14:15.
誰かに 「分かった そういうことは
しないよ」と言われても
He told us to be very careful
when people say,
“I will do this” or “I won’t do this”
at your wedding.
それだけで安心してはいけない
と言われました
Basically, it was up to us to make sure
that the proceedings
結婚式で聖書の原則に外れたことが
起きないようにコントロールするのは
or things that happen at our wedding
私たちの責任だ ということです
would be in order and in harmony
with Bible principles.
もう1つ考えた原則は
Another principle that came to mind was
コリント第一 10:23です
1 Corinthians 10:23.
So obviously, we knew
that we had the right to do many things,
好きなことをする自由はありますが
私たちの結婚式に出席する兄弟姉妹が
どう感じるかを考えました
but we were also very conscious
of how our brothers would view our wedding.
出席する人が誰も気まずい思いをしたり
We didn’t want anybody to be at our wedding
and feel embarrassed
疑問を抱いたりして
ほしくないと思いました
or even stumbled to be there.
Now looking back at our wedding,
振り返って いい結婚式
だったと思います
we look back with fond memories.
聖書の原則を守りながら
So applying Bible principles
didn’t restrict our fun.
楽しいひとときを持てました
出席したみんなが心から楽しめたので
Also, it contributed to the unity
among our brothers
because all of us
—those present, those who were invited—
みんなの絆が強まったと思います
were able to enjoy the wedding.
「あれ？ちょっとまずかったかな？」
と思うことが何も起きなかったので
You’re not worried about thinking,
‘Oh, did that thing offend anybody?’
本当に良い思い出になりました
So you’re able to enjoy the day
without any bad memories.
このように兄弟姉妹は
結婚式や葬式に関連して
As you can see,
our brothers in many countries
are faced with very difficult decisions
非常に難しい決定を
下さなければなりません
where weddings and funerals are concerned.
The guidance the elders
can provide is invaluable.
長老たちのサポートは
大きな助けになります
時々 エホバの証人の患者は
Now, sometimes medical doctors
complain that their Witness patients
are inconsistent
一致していないという
医師の声を聞きます
because they don’t all have the same view
of certain medical treatments.
ある治療についてみんなが
同じ見方をしてはいないからです
One Witness patient
accepts certain fractions or therapies,
1人の患者がある分画や
治療を受け入れると
so the doctor figures he knows
what Jehovah’s Witnesses believe.
医師はエホバの証人の信条が
分かったと考えます
But then the next patient comes along,
でも 次に来た患者は
どれも受け入れません
and he rejects them all.
The doctor is confused.
その医師は混乱します
Those doctors don’t understand
the role of the conscience.
良心の役割を理解していないからです
We shouldn’t worry
when medical professionals
さまざまな見方があるのを医師に
理解されなくても心配は要りません
don’t understand our differing viewpoints,
because we should be glad
that we serve a God
神が私たちに多くのことを
決定する自由を与えて
who dignifies us
with the freedom to make many
尊厳を重んじてくださっていることを
喜べます
of our own decisions.
さて 使徒パウロは
Now, the apostle Paul
mentioned four qualities
平和という絆を保つのに役立つ
4つの性質を挙げました
that will help us to maintain
the uniting bond of peace.
And we’re going to find those qualities
それがエフェソス 4章に
書かれています
at Ephesians chapter 4,
and we’re going to zero in on verse 2.
その2節に注意を向けましょう
Let’s turn to Ephesians chapter 4,
エフェソス 4章をお開きください
and we’re going to look at verse 2.
2節を読みますが
先ほど3-6節を読んで
Now, we read verses 3-6 earlier,
パウロが一致を気に
掛けていることを見ましたね
and you know that Paul
was concerned about unity.
Unity is what he had on his mind,
一致について考えていたパウロはここで
and now he is telling us
that these four qualities
私たちに4つの性質を
教えてくれています
are going to help us to maintain our unity.
それが一致に役立ちます
“Earnestly endeavoring”
「真剣に努力してください」という
言葉を覚えていますか
—remember when he said
“earnestly endeavoring
「一致を保つよう
真剣に努力してください」
to maintain the oneness of the spirit”?
It’s the work that we need
to put into promoting unity.
一致の絆を強めるには努力が必要です
2節です
Verse 2 says:
「いつも謙遜で温和であり
“With all humility and mildness,
“with patience,
辛抱し 愛を抱いて
putting up with one another in love.”
互いに寛容であってください」
Isn’t that beautiful?
You notice the qualities:
humility, mildness,
4つありましたね
謙遜 温和 辛抱 愛です
patience, and love?
When we’re humble,
謙遜であれば 自分の意見がいつも
正しいわけではないことを認めます
we recognize that our opinion
isn’t always the right one.
Humility will also prevent us
謙遜であれば 自分の良心を
人に押し付けようとはしません
from trying to impose
our conscience on others
私たちはエホバから人を裁くようには
任命されていないからです
as if Jehovah had appointed us to judge them.
What about mildness?
次は温和です
Mildness will help us to think
about the effect our words might have
温和であれば 自分の言葉が
兄弟姉妹に与える影響を考えます
on our brothers and sisters.
We would never want to hurt them,
意見が全く一致しない時も
兄弟姉妹を傷つけたくはありません
even when we strongly disagree with them.
And we should give them
the benefit of the doubt.
動機を疑うべきでもありません
If someone says something
that makes you mad,
誰かの言葉で頭にきたなら
話す前に祈ってください
pray before you speak.
Pray before you speak.
話す前に祈ってください
“Love covers a multitude of sins,”
「愛は多くの罪を覆う」ので
which contributes
to the peace of the congregation.
会衆の平和に役立ちます
And we deeply appreciate it
when our brothers are patient with us.
仲間の兄弟が辛抱してくれると
ありがたく感じます
In turn, we need to be patient with them
私たちも辛抱する必要があります
because we’re all
at different stages of spiritual growth,
皆クリスチャンとして同じように
成長しているわけではなく
そのことを認めなければなりません
and we have to acknowledge that.
Well, we’ve talked
about making Jehovah happy
エホバに喜ばれる決定をすること
について話してきました
with our decisions.
会衆の平和のために
頑張ることによっても
We can also please Jehovah
when we work hard
to promote peace in the congregation,
エホバを喜ばせることができます
and sometimes it does take
an earnest endeavor.
時には会衆の平和を保つために
真剣な努力が必要です
Sometimes we have to work hard
at ensuring
that the congregation is at peace.
一生懸命頑張らなければ
ならない時もあります
What about the elders?
特に長老たちは一致し
協力する点で率先します
The elders take the lead
in working together in unity.
They should always speak with a united voice.
語る事柄はいつも一致しているべきです
If they don’t, their congregation
will sense that they’re divided,
そうでないと 会衆の人たちは
それを感じ取り
and this will make
the brothers and sisters uneasy.
兄弟姉妹は落ち着きません
Any difference of opinion
should be worked out in private,
意見の違いは 長老たちだけで
while showing deep respect for one another.
深い敬意を示し合いながら
解決してください
Just because someone disagrees with us
doesn’t make him a bad person.
誰かが同意しないからといって
悪い人と決め付けてはなりません
We have to understand that,
意見の違いによって新しい点に
気付けることもあり
and his difference of opinion
may search us through.
それは皆で考えて検討する
必要のある点かもしれません
It may be something
that we need to think about and consider.
また 相手が正しいかもしれない
といつも考えます
And we always consider
that the other person may be right.
What about us publishers?
クリスチャンは皆
If we’re having a hard time
getting along with someone,
誰かと気が合わないと感じる時
その人を変化させてくださいとではなく
rather than asking Jehovah to change him,
自分を形作ってくださいと
偉大な陶芸家エホバにお願いすべきです
we should ask Jehovah to mold us,
like the Great Potter he is.
We should ask him to show us
why he drew that person to the congregation.
その人を会衆に引き寄せた理由が分かる
ようにしてくださいと祈りましょう
Remember what Jesus said?
イエスは 「父が引き寄せ」た
のでない限り
‘No one comes to him
unless the Father draws him.’
「誰も私のもとに来」れない
と言いました
What does Jehovah see in that person
エホバはその人の内に
私たちに見えていない
that we aren’t seeing?
どんな良い点を見ているのでしょうか
私たち一人一人には
We each have a responsibility to contribute
会衆の平和と一致に
貢献する責任があります
to the peace and unity of the congregation.
May Jehovah bless us
as we work toward that goal.
そうする努力をエホバが
祝福してくださいますように
動機付けを与える話を
どうもありがとうございました
Thank you, Brother Splane,
for that motivating talk!
We are determined to do our part
「平和という絆」を守るために
to safeguard our “uniting bond of peace.”
真剣に努力しようという
気持ちになりました
This session has provided
such practical lessons!
今日も役立つ点を
いろいろ学ぶことができました
What can we look forward to
in the next session?
3日目はどんな内容でしょうか
The theme scripture will be Romans 15:13,
主題聖句はローマ 15:13で
「希望を与える神が⋯⋯
which says in part:
皆さんをあらゆる喜びと
“May the God who gives hope
fill you with all joy and peace.”
平和で満たして
くださ［る］」というものです
The program will feature
a seven-part symposium
7部から成るシンポジウムがあり
平和の種をまいて
with Bible examples of those who sowed
平和を刈り取った
聖書中の人物が取り上げられます
and reaped peace.
We will also want to invite
as many as possible
公開聖書講演を視聴するよう
できるだけ多くの人たちを
招待したいと思います
to enjoy the public Bible discourse entitled
“Friendship With God—How Possible?”
「神と友達になるには」という主題です
Now let’s sing together song number 113,
では ご一緒に113番の歌を
歌いましょう
which draws attention to what it means
to have godly peace.
神からの平和を持つことの意味に
注意を向けています
The song is entitled
歌の題は 「私たちの平和」です
“Our Possession of Peace.”
After the song, you may have
your local concluding prayer.
歌の後 それぞれの場所で
祈りを捧げてください
Again, that’s song number 113.
では113番の歌を歌いましょう